<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The female gallant, or, The wife's the cuckhold a novel.</title>
            <author>Oldys, Alexander.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53318</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15649</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13351962</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13351962</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99196</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53318)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99196)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 469:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The female gallant, or, The wife's the cuckhold a novel.</title>
                  <author>Oldys, Alexander.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 156 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Briscoe ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed Alexander Oldis.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99196:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99196:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Female Gallant OR, THE WIFE'S THE CUCKOLD. A NOVEL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Briſcoe,</hi> over-againſt <hi>Will</hi>'s Coffee-Houſe, in <hi>Ruſſel-Street,</hi> in <hi>Covent-Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99196:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99196:2"/>
            <head>TO My much Eſteemed FRIEND, Mr. <hi>Cardell Goodman.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Wou'd fain ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing new to you in this Dedication; but our Great Maſters in Wit, have already ſo far out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done me, that I muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair
<pb facs="tcp:99196:3"/>
of Entertaining you as I wou'd. To ſay I do not pretend to make you any acknowledgements here, of the Favours I have already receiv'd; becauſe it looks as if I deſign'd to pay a Debt, by borrowing a much greater Sum of the ſame Perſon; is <hi>Old,</hi> tho' 'tis <hi>True.</hi> And for me to attempt here to give the World a Character of <hi>You,</hi> wou'd extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:99196:3"/>
leſſen you; and you wou'd appear like a Great Beauty drawn by a Houſe-daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: And that part of Mankind, which has the happineſs to be <hi>truly</hi> acquainted with you, wou'd throw ſtones at me for my Ignorance, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. Some of that happy number who have needed it, have ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known your Generoſity, nor have I wanted my ſhare of that Knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:99196:4"/>Your Senſe and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have been too Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to be queſtion'd by any <hi>Man</hi> that pretends to either: And they are ſuch as I ought to <hi>dread</hi> upon this Occaſion. You have adorn'd the <hi>Beſt,</hi> and <hi>Higheſt Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters,</hi> and have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times help'd Heaven to make a <hi>Poet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay nothing in
<pb facs="tcp:99196:4"/>
defence of the Diſcourſe I'm going to make you; becauſe it wants more than <hi>I can pretend</hi> to offer for it. Only thus much, that it was really <hi>deſign'd</hi> to pleaſe YOU, and all that read it; as well as to oblige the Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller, and my ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In ſhort, I fear</hi> Sir, you'll find <hi>your Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment but Rude, and Homely;</hi> But I
<pb facs="tcp:99196:5"/>
hope, not <hi>Ill-natur'd,</hi> nor <hi>Uncivil.</hi> You have your Bill of Fare in the Title Page, and if I have dreſs'd any one Diſh <hi>to your Palate,</hi> I wiſh you may make a <hi>Hearty,</hi> but not a <hi>Nauſeous</hi> meal of it; and then I'm ſure <hi>I ſhall be</hi> the <hi>moſt</hi> ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd. You are my Chief Gueſt, Sir, and for <hi>your ſake,</hi> Mr. <hi>Briſcoe</hi> and I are in hopes, that we ſhall have the <hi>Greater
<pb facs="tcp:99196:5"/>
and Better Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</hi> Who, if they bring as much Candour, as I beg you now to be guilty of; with you, will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Sir,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Obliged, and Humble Servant,</hi> Alexander Oldis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:99196:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99196:6"/>
            <head>THE <hi>London Iilt:</hi> OR, THE Female Cuckold.</head>
            <p>SIR <hi>Beetlehead Gripely</hi> liv'd in a great, ugly, old-faſhion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Houſe, ſomewhere in the City; in a Place almoſt as Obſcure as That of his Birth, and <hi>as dark as his Deeds;</hi> and was a Money Scrivener, which (as I am told) is a <hi>devilliſh good Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation.</hi> In this he got, within
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99196:7"/>
the Space of Seven Years, an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of near 12000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed him a Wife of his own Houſhold, worth twice as much for her incomparable Qualities, had ſhe been expos'd to Sale at a more convenient Market. Her Unmarried Names (I won't ſay her <hi>Maiden Names,</hi> though ſhe was his Chamber-maid) were <hi>Winny Wagtail,</hi> of the Great and Notorious Family of the <hi>Wagtails</hi> in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet,</hi> near <hi>Long Acre,</hi> not far from the Square, where, at preſent, I have an Apartment: But, upon her Marriage to Sir <hi>Beetlehead,</hi> ſhe was Dignify'd and Diſtinguiſh'd by the Name and Quality of The Lady <hi>Gripely;</hi> by whom the Knight had Iſſue only <hi>Philandra;</hi> a Lady of moſt Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and Various Qualifications.</p>
            <p>When ſhe was about Eight Years old ſhe went twice a Week,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99196:7"/>
beſides <hi>Sundays,</hi> to hear either the Painful Mr. <hi>B.....</hi> Mr. <hi>D......</hi> or Mr. <hi>F.....</hi> where ſhe would Sigh and Weep as heartily, as if ſhe were already in Love and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair; and would ſing Pſalms till ſhe was e'en Black in the Face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for want of Breath. — (Is not that better than to ſay ſhe ſung like a Nightingale? for I never heard a Nightingale ſing Pſalms.) Theſe Acquiſitions (doubtleſs) ſhe had from her Obſervation of the Pious Lady her Mother, who (poſſibly) had been one of the <hi>Sweet Singers of Iſrael.</hi> At leaſt, we cannot doubt that ſhe was <hi>always one of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of Love.</hi> At Twelve Years of Age, the Beautiful and Zealous <hi>Philandra</hi> could tell who was the Faireſt, who the Strongeſt, and who the Wiſeſt Man, which I hope ſhe has not yet forgot; ſince
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99196:8"/>
they were all for her Turn, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the laſt; for he had moſt Love, moſt Money, and moſt Honour. At Thirteen ſhe could ſay all <hi>Perkin</hi>'s Catechiſm by Rote, both Queſtions and Anſwers; and could give as good an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all the Sermons ſhe heard, as any of thoſe that preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 'em. Beſides, ſhe had a moſt Rapacious Apprehenſion, and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacious Memory of all the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Jeſts and Songs about Town and Court; could quote you any part of the Academy of Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as readily as her Teachers did the Scripture, and apply it more properly, and with leſs A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe. At Fourteen ſhe was ſent to the Boarding-School at <hi>Hackney,</hi> not without the Tutelage of an Old Aunt by her Father's ſide, who died in leſs than a Twelve Month's Time of a Surfeit of thoſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99196:8"/>
Vanities ſhe daily ſaw there. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which, the Niece improv'd to a Miracle in all the Arts of Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry: Though, to give her her due, ſhe was at <hi>Firſt</hi> a very good Proficient in either of 'em; but now, all on a ſuddain, ſhe became moſt perfect in all, in each, and ſingular of 'em. When ſhe ſung, the Angels would ſtand liſtening to her with their Fingers in their Mouths: What then d'you think poor Men would do? Why (Faith) nothing but hold their peace, that they might the better hear her; and ſilently wiſh, that they had the ſpoiling of ſo good a Voice. When ſhe Danc'd, the Sparks have ſworn that ſhe was Begotten by <hi>Mercury:</hi> And I am apt to believe it; for, Men ſay her Father was a Thief by his Vocation, — But their Reaſon was, becauſe ſhe mov'd, as if ſhe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99196:9"/>
had Wings at her Feet. When ſhe Writ a <hi>Billette doux,</hi> ſhe did it with more Elegancy and Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs than Madam <hi>Scaron</hi> [or <hi>Maintenon.</hi>] When ſhe Dictated to Madam <hi>Monteſpan,</hi> the Letters ſhe writ to <hi>Louis Le Grand.</hi> In ſhort, ſhe had an abundance of Grace in all her Words and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but the Devil a bit in all her Thoughts. Yet this I am oblig'd to ſay for her, that, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all theſe Egregious Acquiſitions, and Extraordinary Imbelliſhments, ſhe was not <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually</hi> Proud, though the World may believe, by the Sequel, that ſhe was <hi>Carnally</hi> Proud; witneſs the ſeveral Intrigues ſhe had at the Chaſte Boarding-School, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe came to Converſe in this Leud Town and Court: Not that ſhe ever <hi>finiſh'd</hi> one, till a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Eighteenth Year of her
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99196:9"/>
Tyranny. As to her Perſon, ſhe was really very Beautiful, being extreamly like our late Famous Dutcheſs now in <hi>France,</hi> as near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſembling her as the Knight of <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> or my ſelf, reſemble the Figure of the late Incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Scaron;</hi> and ſhe was as Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as t'other for the Heart of her.</p>
            <p>While ſhe was under Education, among the reſt, Sir <hi>Blunder Slouch</hi> was her daily Votary. A Spark every way accompliſh'd to bear the Marks of his Wife's Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to another Man; of a moſt eaſie and credulous Nature to the fair Sex; a tall, heavy, cold, phlegmatick Booby; a great Coward, and very Rich; by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion a <hi>Norwich</hi> Factor; a great Favourite of Sir <hi>Beetlehead</hi>'s, ſo like him in his Intellects, Religion and Morals, that <hi>Gripely</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99196:10"/>
ſince he was not his own lawfully begotten Son, he ſhould be his Son by Marriage; which (doubtleſs) he had brought to Perfection, had the Old Man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved but a Quarter of a Year longer.</p>
            <p>Beſides this <hi>Slouch</hi> you may be pleaſed to obſerve, that in the long and tedious Catalogue of her Adorers, there was found, as Ringleader of all thoſe her well-affected Subjects and Slaves, the Lord <hi>Bellamant,</hi> a Beau of the Firſt Rate, a young, beautiful Spark, of true Courage and Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, and of near 5000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> a Year Eſtate; of Wit and Humour enough to accompliſh any thing he undertook. He and his Siſter were Twins, wherefore (as I am told) they were born much about the ſame time. At moſt (as I am credibly inform'd by the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99196:10"/>
Learned in ſuch Caſes) there could not be a Quarter of a Year's Difference in their Age: And they were ſo paſſing alike, that one of his Legs was not more like t'other, than ſhe was to him, though his Legs were both equally proportionable and handſome. Their Stature was equal, their Complexion the ſame, being exceeding Fair; the Tone of their Voices alike ſoft and charming; each had a Mole on the Right Cheek, but his was not ſo obvious to Sight, becauſe of his Perruke, and therefore rarely taken notice of. Their Thoughts and Paſſions proceeded as from one Soul; only Nature and different Education, according to their Sexes, had given <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella</hi> (for that was her Name if you'll believe me; or, if you don't, I cann't tell how you'll be better ſatisfied) a greater ſhare of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99196:11"/>
Modeſty and ſtrictneſs of Vertue than her Brother.</p>
            <p>On this Extraordinary Man <hi>Philandra</hi> thought ſhe had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd her deceitful Heart: Nay and, I dare ſay, at ſometimes ſhe did moſt paſſionately and intirely love him. Letters paſt daily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em, while ſhe was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her yet innocent Exerciſes. But — as the Devil would ha't, (who ow'd her a ſpite, though I cann't tell for what; for, I'll be ſworn, ſhe never diſoblig'd him <hi>wittingly</hi> in all her Life) one Day, as ſhe was Dancing, ſhe dropp'd a Letter which ſhe had written in Anſwer to one of the Lord <hi>Bella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant</hi>'s; and who ſhould take it up but that damn'd, eternal Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb, Sir <hi>Blunder,</hi> who was moſt plaguily Aſſiduous in his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits to her, eſpecially on Dancing Days. The Booby (it ſeems)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99196:11"/>
could Read; and finding it In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrb'd <hi>To the Lord Bellamant,</hi> whom he had ſeen there Twice or Thrice, began to be troubled with a ſwelling at his Noſe, having ſome reaſonable Jealouſie, that <hi>Bellamant</hi> dreſs'd and talk'd ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what finer than he; though he could not allow him to be half ſo proper a Fellow — The witty Dog concealing his Reſentments, clapp'd the Letter into his Pocket, as rightly imagining ſhe would never look for it there: Nor truly did ſhe miſs it, till he had the Opportunity of Reading it as he was going for <hi>London</hi> in his Hackney Coach; when, relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it from the fulſome Company of his Bills and Bonds, he found under Hand and Seal theſe Words following:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99196:12"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>IF your Lordſhip could aſſure me, that what you have ſaid and written to me, were not a piece of Gallantry natural to you, and in Courſe to all young Creatures of our eaſie Sex, I ſhould certainly have Reaſon to think my ſelf the happieſt Creature breathing in your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's Eſteem; however, be your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs real or feign'd, it appears ſo Advantageouſly for you, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but wiſh, that you did ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely Love</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>PHILANDRA.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Uds Fives and Nines! (cry'd <hi>Slouch</hi> aloud) here's fine work! Are you taken with your fine Show! A poor, young Fellow, hardly Nineteen, with ne're a hair
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99196:12"/>
upon his Chin; and becauſe (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) he can Dance! Soft and Fair! This Pace will never carry it. — Yet how ſhall I prevent it? — Oh! — I think I've found it out. — He's a Rank Papiſh, and Sir <hi>Beetlehead</hi> hates a Papiſh as bad as I do; which I do as utterly as Plain-dealing and Poverty. But if ſhe Loves him, what then? — Why let 'em Marry in the Devil's Name, ſo I can but get her Father to diſinhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit her; (which I ſhould not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of in the leaſt were it not for her Mother; who is as Wanton, and altogether Vain, as ſhe. In this perplexity he got at laſt to <hi>Gripely</hi>'s old Enchanted Caſtle, where a great many Widows and Orphans lay Bound in <hi>Vellum and Paper</hi> ſo faſt, that 'tis not expected they ſhould e'er get looſe till Doom's-day, when, 'tis thought,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99196:13"/>
they may Hamper <hi>Him:</hi> But the old Fellow thinks 'tis a great while hence, and means to make all the preſent uſe of his Money that he can. Juſt at the Hall Door the Two Villains encountred; <hi>Slouch</hi> accoſted the old One with a Face full of Concern, contrary to what he was wont coming from <hi>Philandra,</hi> inſomuch that Sir <hi>Beetlehead</hi> himſelf took notice of it: What's the Matter Sir <hi>Blunder?</hi> (ſaid he) How does my Daughter? Not ſo well as ſhe ſhould, (reply'd t'other) or as you would have her, I fear. How! how! (cry'd the Father) what mean you, Sir <hi>Blunder?</hi> Explain your ſelf, ('pray) for I am in the Dark. (Which, no doubt, he was in any part of that curs'd Fabrick, without the help of Artificial Lights.) This Paper your Daughter dropp'd (ſaid Sir
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99196:13"/>
               <hi>Blunder</hi>) and I took it up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to her; out of which if you can pick any thing to your Satisfaction, I pray do. Sir. The old Man, taking the Letter, was forc'd to go into the Back-Parlour, that look'd into a Neighbour's Garden; where, by the help of Four Eyes, he made a ſhift to read it aloud in his Lady's hearing. At the end of it he rav'd out, Uds precious, my Lady! Theſe are wicked Times indeed, when our Children are plotting the Ruine of their Parents, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving the Infirmity of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. The Infamy, you mean, (interrupted ſhe.) But where's the hurt of this? For I underſtand the Buſineſs. What if the Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi> have a Paſſion for her, and ſhe for him? Where's the danger of it? He is a Perſon of Honour, he has a good Eſtate,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99196:14"/>
and is a riſing Man at Court. For my part, I could wiſh 'twere a Match. How, Madam, (cry'd <hi>Slouch</hi> rudely) Why he's a Papiſh! Ay, he's a Papiſh, my Lady! (echo'd the old dry Trunk) What of that? (ſaid the young Lady of about Forty) Is not King <hi>James</hi> our Sovereign a Papiſt? No, no, my Lady (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd Threeſcore and Twelve) he is a Roman Catholick. That's the ſame Thing (ſaid ſhe.) You'll pardon me, my Lady (returned <hi>Gripely</hi>) for every Subject who is that way given, though he were a Duke, is a Papiſh; and the King and Queen only are Roman Catholicks. Well but (interru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted ſhe) what danger do you apprehend from your Daughter's Marrying to this Papiſt-Lord? What danger? (cry'd the old Knight, ſtraining his Voice; which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99196:14"/>
threw him into a violent Fit of Coughing, that forc'd out one of his Nine Teeth.) Uds pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, my Lady! why; Fire, and Faggot, and Gun-powder, and Squibs, and Crackers, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and Devils, and Papiſts, would continually be Buzzing and Sputtering about our Ears; and not a Corner of our Houſe would be free from a Dark Lanthorn. No, no, I'll ha' no Papiſh Son-in-Law I can aſſure you, my Lady. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Reins</hi> our Butler, Porter, Groom and Coachman ſhall make ready the Coach, and I'll fetch her Home to Night before to Morrow. Indeed, Madam (ſaid <hi>Slouch</hi>) 'tis the only way to prevent the Ruine both of her Soul and Body. Why of her Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? (ask'd the Lady-Mother) good Sir <hi>Blunder!</hi> mayn't a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Lord <hi>Do</hi> as well as a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99196:15"/>
Knight? But — no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter — if my Lovy Sir <hi>Beetle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> is reſolve t have her home, I hope I may bear him Company to fetch her. With all his own poor Heart, (replied <hi>Gripely,</hi> chucking her under the Chin.) Thou art my dear Bird, and my moſt Kind and Dutiful Lady-Wife. Sir <hi>Blunder</hi> (ſaid the Lady) I ſuppoſe you may ſpare your ſelf the Trouble of a ſecond Viſit to my Daughter this Day. She will have time enough to thank you for your Care at her Return. <hi>Slouch</hi> was not altogether ſuch a Booby, but he perceived it was a kind of Reprimand by the manner of her Addreſs to him: Wherefore he only made a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſlovenly bow. And they proceeded in their ſhort, but tedious Journey. You may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve 'twas tedious to the Lady-Mother,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99196:15"/>
becauſe <hi>Reins</hi> was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to drive very ſlowly and gently, for fear of breaking, or at leaſt disjointing, his Aged Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's Bones.</p>
            <p>No ſooner had Sir <hi>Blunder</hi> had his Audience of Congé at the Boarding-School, than <hi>Philandra</hi> was accoſted with the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Reſpects of a ſtrange Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, who fell paſſionately in Love with her there that very Afternoon; who, though he was not Dignified with any Title of Honour, or Quality, above that of a Gentleman, yet was eminently diſtinguiſh'd from moſt of his Degree, by an Eſtate of near 6000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> a Year; and add to this the Advantages of his Perſon, Mind, and Education; which were all very extraordinary; and you will conclude he muſt certainly ſucceed in any Amorous Attempt.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99196:16"/>
You muſt be acquainted with him by the Name of <hi>Worthygrace;</hi> which Name his Family had born time out of mind. — (Faith) I cannot particularly tell you how long, but you may aſſure your ſelf 'twas ever ſince they were ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. He had inquired (it ſeems) of her Birth and Fortune: The laſt of which (poſſibly) he lik'd as well almoſt as her Perſon. Their Circumſtances was moſt agreeable in every point, but one; and that was in Age: For he was near Thirty, and ſhe not Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen. Madam (ſaid he, approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her with Mr. <hi>Stepwell</hi> her Dancing-Maſter, who had the Honour of his Acquaintance) I come to make my moſt humble Acknowledment to you, of the greateſt Obligation that you could poſſibly place on a Perſon, which is yet ſo perfectly miſerable as to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99196:16"/>
be altogether unknown to you. Sir, <hi>(reply'd the Fair Falſe One)</hi> your Diſcourſe is abſolutely as ſtrange to me, as your Perſon; yet, tho' they are both ſurpriſing, I will not call 'em troubleſome; nor ſhall I be yet Curious to know what the Obligation is you talk of: Yes, Madam, <hi>(In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted he)</hi> it is but neceſſary you ſhou'd be ſenſible, that you are the ſole occaſion of my making the beſt uſe of all my Travels; ſince, for your ſake alone, I return moſt paſſionately in Love with my own Country. I ſee, Sir, (<hi>return'd</hi> Philandra) you take the liberty of a Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; and I hope, I ſhall not hazard my Salvation in not believing you. If you wou'd make more uſe of your Reaſon, Madam, <hi>(re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd he)</hi> and leſs of your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, I am confident you wou'd
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99196:17"/>
be of my Faith: However, if you will not, I ſhall endeavour by all the moſt conſtant and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Reſpects of your moſt Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Adorers, to let you ſee, that I muſt Dye in this Truth, without a poſſibility of being convinc'd in my Perſwaſion of it. I am ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Sir, <hi>(reply'd ſhe)</hi> that you are ſo obſtinately reſolv'd to Dye in a Hereſie, tho' it ſhou'd be really at preſent, your unhappy Opinion. A great deal more of ſuch ſtuff paſs'd between 'em; but I hope, I am not oblig'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it all: At the end of which, or (unhappily) before, the Old Grey Puſs, or Governeſs of the Houſe, call'd her aſide; for ſhe watch'd her as narrowly, as a Cat does a Mouſe. At this unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected interruption, our good Friend <hi>Worthygrace</hi> had like to have loſt himſelf and all Patience,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99196:17"/>
and was about to have made ſome Outlandiſh Prayers for her; that ſound as loud as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and might have ſignifi'd as well no doubt, but he pay'd her with thinking. Yet, to ſpeak truly of him, he was not ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful as Amorous: So that, he thought it more neceſſary to apply himſelf to <hi>Stepwell</hi> for a ſecond interview, than to an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary for <hi>Arſenick</hi> for the Old Cat.</p>
            <p>He had not been a Traveller for above Ten years together, without having Learn'd what was the beſt Speech, wherefore he Addreſs'd to the <hi>Maître de Dance,</hi> in the moſt Elegant Dialect of an Hundred Guineas, which did his Buſineſs to ſome Tune, as far as it lay in Monſieur <hi>Coupé</hi>'s Talent. Let us leave 'em then, hatching their Egg for this young Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99196:18"/>
who was now retir'd into her Chamber, where ſhe began to ſearch for her Letter to the Lord <hi>Bellamant,</hi> in order (perhaps) to Examine and Correct it.—But (Ah, unparrallell'd Misfortune!) ſhe might as ſoon have found the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans</hi> in her Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom; which I dare ſay, never came nearer her Dainty, White, Smooth, Downy, (what ſhall I ſay!) Skin, than her Pocket or Glove, unleſs it were at her fingers ends.—She caus'd her Attendant to undo her Gown, unlace her Stays, and ſhe her ſelf peeping down her Shift, expos'd ſuch Beauties to the God of Day, as had he then been as young as when he purſu'd <hi>Daphne,</hi> he had certainly left her for the Fairer Prize <hi>Philandra;</hi> nor (I fancy) wou'd ſhe have been half ſo skit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh.—What d'you call this now?
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99196:18"/>
A Flight?—'Tis a fine thing to have Read!—A Flight let it be then, becauſe one ran away.—But all this Beauty and all theſe Charms, cou'd not charm back her Letter to her. No, I can't tell, whether <hi>Gadbury, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge,</hi> or <hi>Coley,</hi> cou'd have Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd it from Old <hi>Gripely;</hi> for he was ſurely a greater Devil than any they deal with; ſuppoſing, they piſs in a Quill with Satan himſelf: And now were the Stars call'd to account for their inad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertency, in a matter ſo nearly concerning her; but whether they heard or not, I will not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively ſay; tho' it is my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that her Siſter <hi>Venus</hi> ſent it to her again, by the hand of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn;</hi> yet contrary to my expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or deſire; for juſt as he was in the heighth of Deſpair and Rage, Enters Old <hi>Gripely,</hi> and her
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99196:19"/>
own Dear Lady Mother: Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>(cry'd the Old Teſty Knight)</hi> (I can't ſay Gentleman) look you, here's a Letter for you, 'tis worth your notice, but you muſt ſtay to Read it till you come home.— In the mean time <hi>(purſued he, turning to her Servant)</hi> Maiden, pack up your young Lady's Trumpery and your own; that we may take 'em along with us in the Coach. Upon ſight of the Superſcription, <hi>Philandra</hi> ſoon gueſs'd how it dropt from her Boſome into her Father's hands. O baſe, Unbred, boobily Fellow, <hi>(cry'd ſhe to her ſelf aſide)</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray this unfortunate Paper to more unlucky hands. Nay, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>(Interrupted her Mother who overheard her, and ſpoke ſoftly)</hi> moſt unmindful and regardleſs Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo to Diſpoſe of what might for ever Oblige or Ruine thee:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99196:19"/>
But no more, reſtrain your Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I'le ſee to compoſe all this to your Satisfaction. Come (<hi>cry'd Old</hi> Gripely) we'll take a fair leave of your Miſtreſs, and you may bid farewel to your School-fellows; by that time <hi>Mariana</hi> will have got all things ready. Juſt at theſe words, in came the Old Beldame, with her ſhaking Head, and her Heart trembling, for the loſs of ſo good a Scholar; which ſhe learn'd from <hi>Reins,</hi> was to be the ungrateful Conſequence of this unſeaſonable Viſit; and while the Parents were making their Apology, for ſo unexpectedly taking home their Daughter; <hi>Philandra</hi> made ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ft unperceiv'd, to convey a little Cabinet Cramm'd with Epiſtles of her Lovers, to a young Lady ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times her Bedfellow and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, whom ſhe inſtructed, how
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99196:20"/>
and when to diſpoſe of it; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning time enough to receive her Governeſſe's Sage Advice and Prayers; to whom ſhe return'd thanks in <hi>Gales of Sighs, and Floods of Tears;</hi> to think, ſhe muſt now loſe thoſe dear oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of Hearing and Relating with ſeveral of thoſe pretty young Creatures her School-fellows, how often, how near, each of 'em were <hi>only like</hi> to have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, thro' ſome malicious diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of their Cruel Stars, which had more care of their Happineſs than they themſelves; beſides a thouſand other ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, which now ſhe fear'd ſhe muſt forego.</p>
            <p>But to be ſhort,—home they got about Nine at Night; where her Father gave her a round rally, which ſhe took ſo much to Heart, as ſhe went to Bed, and reſolv'd
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99196:20"/>
not to ſee the Sun, as long— as—ſhe ſtay'd within doors. (which Reſolution ſhe cou'd not avoid keeping, unleſs ſhe got to the top of the Houſe in a fair day; and then you'l ſay (perhaps) ſhe was not within doors.) But ſhe really kept her Bed for three or four days, and affected a deep Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, which was at length attended by an ugly Diſtemper, call'd the <hi>Itch of Gadding Abroad.</hi> In the Cure of this, her Pious Lady Mother was very inſtrumental; for after having caus'd her to be let Blood, (which then was not very unſeaſonable, the Summer being very moderate) and after one Doſe of Pills, with ſome Good, Coſtly, and Comfortable Cordials, ſhe eaſily prevail'd with Mr. <hi>Phyſmacary,</hi> (who was both Doctor and Pothecary in Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to that Bleſſed Family) to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99196:21"/>
agree with her, that it was moſt expedient her Daughter ſhou'd take a little freſh Air. This was eaſily accorded to by Old <hi>Gripely,</hi> for he knew that ten miles of the beſt Air, wou'd not coſt him half ſo much, as two Ounces of the worſt Cordial; and the next day was prefix'd for it.</p>
            <p>During the Malignancy of her Diſtemper, which reign'd chiefly in her Head, (where it does in moſt People of her Youth, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and Circumſtances) the Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi> had been to pay his Devoirs to her at the Boarding School: There he heard of her ſuddain removal; which tho' at firſt, it ſtartled him, yet on ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts he propos'd greater advantages to himſelf by it. And his laſt Deſign was to get his Twin-Siſter <hi>Arabella,</hi> to Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany <hi>Aurelia, Philandra</hi>'s ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99196:21"/>
Bedfellow and Confident, in a Viſit to her; which ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the Afternoon. She was <hi>once again, at leaſt,</hi> to be bleſt with the ſight of the <hi>Gay World,</hi> and the Scent of the Court Air, intending for St. <hi>James</hi>'s Park. You may imagine, ſhe was not a little pleas'd at the ſight of her Dear Confident, and of the Lady <hi>Arabella;</hi> which laſt brought the Beauties of the Lord her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo freſh in her Memory, that <hi>Philandra</hi> had like to have fallen into a fit of Sickneſs indeed: To think it was not that <hi>Subſtantia<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Figure ſhe would have ſeen at her Bed-ſide, or rather have Embrac'd in her Bed. After the two young Ladies had condol'd with the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Gripley,</hi> who was ſtill preſent, the cruel Malady of her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; the indulgent Mother, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by her own paſt Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99196:22"/>
that the preſence of a Parent might cauſe ſome reſtraint in their Freedome of Diſcourſe, very Modeſtly and Kindly withdrew; <hi>Philander</hi>'s Attendant waiting on her to the door, ſhe not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her Daughter the trouble of that Ceremony: By which means <hi>Arabella</hi> had the opportunity of preſenting <hi>Philandra</hi> with a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which her Brother had truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her diſcreet mannagement, to deliver to <hi>Philandra</hi>'s own fair hands; which, tho' at all times they were exceeding fair, yet, now, by this white,—as— (Ah! wou'd my Shirt, ay, or my Crevat, were as white!) the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Snow, for ſhe had us'd a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Ointment, and lay in Dog-skin-Gloves, with her Arms ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended over her Head all this while, unleſs when any Viſitors came.—(I believe, I can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99196:22"/>
you a Receipt of the Oyntments to oblige you, Ladies; for I know Mr. <hi>Phyſmacary</hi> very well) But now ſhe pull'd off one of her Gloves to receive the <hi>Billett doux;</hi> which yet ſhe cou'd not Read, becauſe of the ſuddain return of her Attendant: Wherefore ſhe conceal'd it in her Bed, till a more convenient time. However ſhe ſent as proper an anſwer to it, as if ſhe had perus'd it a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times over: Telling the Ladys, that ſhe was advis'd to breath a little freſh Air; and, that on the Morrow her Lady <hi>Mother</hi> and ſhe deſign'd for St. <hi>James</hi>'s Park; where ſhe ſhou'd be happy to meet ſuch excellent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany as their Ladyſhips about four in the Afternoon. The Lady <hi>Arabella</hi> ſoon took the hint; and promis'd ſhe wou'd endeavour to divert her by the beſt means in her Capacity: (Which, ſhe knew, was by bringing her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,) And immediately upon this, ſhe and <hi>Aurelia</hi> Kiſs'd her fair Cheek; and ſo Commending her to Heaven's Care, quitted the Room; why <hi>Fair</hi> Cheek now you'l ſay (perhaps!) Why:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99196:23"/>
let it be ſoft, Roſy, or Fair, I care not which, 'tis not a pin matter, but <hi>one</hi> of 'em it muſt be, in <hi>my</hi> Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.—No ſooner was <hi>Mariana,</hi> her Attendant, gone to wait on the Ladys down Stairs, but <hi>Philandra</hi> Raviſhed the Letter from between the Sheets; and, after having thrice Kiſs'd it, ſhe ſaw on the outſide theſe words, <hi>To the Charming</hi> Philandra: In the inſide ſhe found he expreſſed himſelf thus,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> cannot <hi>think</hi> (Madam) nor I <hi>expreſs</hi> what dreadful Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions I had at firſt, of your haſty, and, I fear unvoluntary Retreat from <hi>Hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney;</hi> which had like to have terminated in an utter Deſpair of ever ſeeing you more. And had not Love inſpir'd me, beyond my own Dull Capacity, to engage my ſelf to deliver my Soul with this into your Dear Hands, I had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly left all the Pleaſures of <hi>this</hi> World, and, which is moſt valuable in it, your ſelf, for a Monaſtick Life Which tho' it may ſuit with Religion; (I fancy) will hardly ever agree with my
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99196:23"/>
Complexion. If then (Madam) you will preſerve me from being Bury'd Alive; let me, I beſeech you, know by her, where and when I may ſee and adore that Divinity which alone gives Life and Reliſh to all the joys of <hi>(Madam)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours Eternally, BELLAMANT.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>After ſhe had again Kiſs'd it thrice; ſhe faſten'd it, by an Engine very much in uſe among Ladys, to the Veil of Love's Temple; In plain Engliſh, to her ſhift: Thinking ſhe had now ſecur'd <hi>that</hi> from all poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of an eſcape from her: And, that ſhe had it as faſt, as ſhe held the Heart of him that ſent it. Soon after ſhe had thus plac'd the Copy of my Lord's Heart on her left ſide, next her own; her Lady-Mother uſher'd in Sir <hi>Blunder,</hi> who of all <hi>Men,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept her Father, had the priviledge to viſit her in her Bed-Chamber; and whom, except her Father, ſhe hated above all Men. (For to ſay truth, <hi>Slouch</hi> was not ſo Old, by near forty years) At the ſight of him
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99196:24"/>
ſhe began to look as Pale as the Moon; when, juſt before, ſhe was as Ruddy and Glorious as the Sun. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Philandra</hi> (ſaid he) I come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole the tedious Fit of Sickneſs you have had: And (truly) had it not been for troubling you; I wou'd have viſited you oftner and ſooner. 'Tis <hi>now</hi> too ſoon, (returned ſhe) unleſs you deſign to compleat by your <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> what you had but begun by your <hi>Curioſity:</hi> I mean, my Death. I compleat your Death (interrupted he) I profeſs, I never thought of ſuch a thing, days of my Breath. No matter (returned ſhe, mocking him) I profeſs, there is never another Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for you.—(How if ſhe ſhou'd miſtake now?) why, Madam <hi>Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> (replyed he) I thought no more harm when I gave Sir <hi>Beetlehead</hi> your Letter; than an Apple's like an Oyſter. At this Simile ſhe cou'd hardly forbear laughing <hi>aloud:</hi> while he went on much to the ſame tune. In good truth, I delivered it to him becauſe you were not at home; that he might ſend it to you again, or to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99196:24"/>
my Lord <hi>Bellamant:</hi> For, upon my Truly now, Madam <hi>Philandra,</hi> I am as ready to ſerve you, as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row out of a Bow. And whom cou'd I better entruſt with your Secrets than your own dear Father? One wou'd <hi>think</hi> you were in the right on't, in truſting my own Dear Father with a jeaſting piece of Gallantry of mine that I wou'd not have had him ſee: But I muſt needs own, 'twas an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent contrivance, and much like your own Dear Worſhipful ſelf, to carry my Letter <hi>from</hi> me, that it might be ſent <hi>to</hi> me. Say, was not this for Expeditions ſake? In good Faith (anſwered the Booby) I thought to have given it you again, aſſoon as I had read it; but forgot it.—In good Faith I did.—(Now Pox upon him, for an unhappy ſilly Dog. For he makes my Heart ake. Since juſt ſo us'd the Reverend Old Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to ſay to me:— In good Faith (Child) I muſt whip thee.) But with a ſcornful ſmile (ſhe return'd) in good Faith Sir, I thank you, that after you had expos'd to all
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99196:25"/>
the Senſe you had, what I wou'd have conceal'd to you and almoſt all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind beſide; you wou'd have vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaf'd to have return'd it me, had you not forgotten it. O, Admirable piece of Civility and Breeding! So Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous an Act, ſure was never commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any Villain that takes your Purſe, ſure! What! My Lady (ſaid he) do's Madam <hi>Philandra</hi> call me <hi>Villain!</hi>—I am afraid, ſhe is not in her right Maidenly Wits. Indeed I fear ſo too (replyed the Mother) ſhe has been delirious all along ſince ſhe kept her Bed: Theſe kind of Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers make 'em all ſo. Wherefore I wou'd adviſe and entreat you to leave me alone with her: Happily, I may help her to compoſe her ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thoughts. Your Servant, my Lady: Goodnight, ſweet Madam <hi>Philandra</hi> (ſaid he) and made a Leg, going out. So;—Heav'n be prais'd! my worſt Diſtempers gone: (cry'd the young Lady) not Poverty with all it's worſt Attendants is half ſo bad, as to be yok'd to thee.</p>
            <p>Can you, my Honour'd Mother, ſuffer it?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:99196:25"/>
               <hi>When e're you ſee me Bedded with this Slave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Say, He's my</hi> Monument, <hi>the Bed my</hi> Grave.</p>
            <p>Here our <hi>Sappho</hi> let looſe whole floods of Briny-Salt tears, as <hi>Round</hi> and <hi>Clear</hi> as ſo many Pearls: But (Pardon me, Ladyes!) not altogether ſo <hi>Precious,</hi> in <hi>my</hi> poor judgement. At the ſight of this inundation, which were enough to ſet any <hi>Young</hi> Man's Heart a Fire, (and that's ſtrange you'l ſay) the Lady-Mother dropp'd an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril-ſhower; which was not of long Continuance: And, after they both had wept, they both ſmil'd: The Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous indulgent Mother aſſuring the <hi>Angel-like</hi> Daughter, (I mean, for Beauty) that ſhe wou'd never ſuffer it; nor cou'd ever live to ſee it. <hi>Philandra</hi> proceeded then to make an ingenuous Confeſſion of the Paſſion ſhe had for the Lord <hi>Bellamant;</hi> begging her pardon, that ſhe had hitherto kept her a ſtranger to it. Who told her, in <hi>that only</hi> ſhe was to blame, for (ſaid ſhe) I like his Perſon and Eſtate
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99196:26"/>
very well. But <hi>above all</hi> his Title: For, if you Marry <hi>Him;</hi> you'l be a better Woman than my Lady <hi>May'reſs:</hi> And you ſhall take place of her any where on Engliſh Ground; unleſs in the City, I fear.—The <hi>Bellamants</hi> (continued ſhe) are as Ancient and Great a Family as any in the four Kingdoms; when I was about your Age, I was <hi>Intimately</hi> acquainted with above a ſcore of 'em: And, I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, they were all fine Gentlemen: Some, very Proper, Handſom, Luſty Men: Others, Midleſiz'd and Brisk Men: Some again little Pretty Sprite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Creatures: All of 'em, Brave Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous, Active, and High-mettll'd Men.—Ay; ay (added ſhe) I am clearly for a <hi>Bellamant,</hi> and I warrant thee (my Dear) we'll carry the day: Therefore ſatisfie thy ſelf, and take a hearty repoſe: This Kiſs and a good Night to thee: A thouſand good-nights to my Dear and Honour'd Mother, (ſaid <hi>Philandra,</hi> as her Mother left her.) All this while that Treacherous Jade <hi>Mariana</hi> had overheard their Diſcourſe; which ſhe was to repeat
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99196:26"/>
to <hi>Slouch,</hi> having been retain'd by him with five Guinea's and ſeveral Nights Lodgings; which, at long run, coſt him a heavier Summ. A little time after her Mother was gone, <hi>Philandra</hi> fell aſleep <hi>Hand over Head;</hi> never <hi>Dreaming</hi> that her Attendant had ſuch true Ears, and ſo falſe a Heart: But 'twas no wonder; for, Sir <hi>Blunder</hi> had had the managment of her for above a Month <hi>before</hi> he preferr'd her to <hi>Philandra;</hi> whom ſhe had not ſerv'd longer than four Months.</p>
            <p>About twelve a Clock the next day the Lady <hi>Gripely</hi> thought it convenient her Daughter ſhou'd riſe: Allowing two hours for Dreſſing, an hour for Dining, and about as much for their journey for the Park: So, <hi>Philandra</hi> call'd for freſh Linnen, and up ſhe got. Her thoughts were ſo wholly intent on the Adventure ſhe was like to have that Afternoon, that ſhe quite forgot the Letter which ſhe had faſten'd to her Shift, and after Dinner took Coach without it. For, this Damn'd Maid Woman (Whore I was going
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99196:27"/>
to ſay) taking the Shift, to lay it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide; prick'd her Finger with the Pin that held it there: Which when ſhe had taken out, the Letter fell on the Ground before her. She immediately took it up, and gave it to <hi>Slouch,</hi> who came preſently after he had Din'd to Sir <hi>Beetlehead</hi>'s, as was his Cuſtom: And withal made him a repetition of what ſhe had overheard in Diſcourſe between the Mother and Daughter; ſoon afterwards ſhe was call'd to wait on her Lady to the Park. There were only thoſe four who went in <hi>that</hi> Coach; the Lady <hi>Gripely, Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> and <hi>Mariana,</hi> (I warrant you think that I can't count four as I ſhou'd do) but you may be pleas'd to take notice, that <hi>Mariana</hi> was with Child of a <hi>Slouch;</hi> and more than half gone. Well; to the Park they got, juſt as the Guards were reliev'd; and, in ſome few Minutes after, Sir <hi>Blunder</hi> arriv'd there, in his <hi>own Hackney Coach;</hi> (for he was too miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to keep one: Tho' he was as Proud as any Beggerly upſtart-Citizen in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi>) when he was got
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:99196:27"/>
through the Horſe-Guards, (which (no doubt) he curs'd in his Heart, becauſe they were King <hi>James</hi>'s, and the Lord <hi>Dover</hi>'s Troop too that were then upon Duty.) He took the Walk on the Left Hand by the Bird-Cage; which (as it happen'd) was the right way to meet the Ladys; who were gotten by this time about the middle of the Mall, juſt over againſt St. <hi>James</hi>'s Houſe, when they met the Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi> and the Lady his Siſter, Attended only by her Women and two Footmen. After the firſt Saluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Bellamant</hi> addreſſed himſelf to the Mother. Telling he that that Part of the World did bretter ſuit with Ladys of ſo Great Beauty and Gallantry than the Dull, Preciſe, and unmannerly City, which they only made happy and valuable by their Reſidence in it, more than it's <hi>Wealth</hi> and <hi>Traffick in the World.</hi> To which the Lady <hi>Gripely</hi> reply'd, that it was <hi>therefore</hi> the moſt advantagious place for them to live in, ſince there, their want of Breeding and Humour was the leſs obſervable. I never thought,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99196:28"/>
Madam (return'd the Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi>) that I <hi>cou'd</hi> have been ſo unhappy as not to ſubſcribe to ev'ry <hi>particular</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of your Ladyſhip's, till this unlucky Moment: But, Madam (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he, applying himſelf to <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra</hi>) I am yet more unfortunately miſtaken, if you don't think this Air more agreeable to the Sweetneſs of your Complexions, than the Smoaky Climat of <hi>that, ſtill unſatisfy'd, and unhallow'd,</hi> tho' <hi>pretended,</hi> Sanctify'd Place. And I fear, Madam (added he) that your apprehenſions of ſuch a retreat from the Gay World, threw you into a Melancholly, which might have been no leſs fatal to me, and all the admiring World, than to your Ladyſhip; had not Heaven preſerv'd <hi>the neareſt Copy of it ſelf in you,</hi> to be ador'd by all Mankind—My Lord (ſaid <hi>Philandra</hi>) I did really Arm my ſelf againſt all <hi>Modeſty,</hi> e're I came abroad, <hi>expecting,</hi> indeed, to receive ſuch Volleys of your Wit and Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry.—She had gone on ſtill; had not <hi>Stopwell,</hi> approaching 'em with Mr. <hi>Worthygrace,</hi> and his Equipage,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99196:28"/>
prevented her.—My moſt Honour'd Lady! (cry'd he out aloud) and my Divine Miſtreſs <hi>Philandra!</hi> How hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py am I to ſee your Ladyſhip ſo well recover'd in your Health and Beauty, as to adorn this Walk with what it ſo long has wanted in your abſence?— Madam (interrupted <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) Mr. <hi>Stopwell</hi> wrongs the Court-Ladies; ſome of which are really Great Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, who frequently do bleſs this Park. But, pardon me, Madam I beſeech you, if I think <hi>you</hi> have done 'em the greater injury; in appearing h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſo much to their diſadvantage,— 'Sdeath!—what Spark's this? (crys <hi>Bellamant</hi> to himſelf; with a jealous frown and an angry bluſh) but ſtraight recalling himſelf (ſaid he to <hi>Worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace</hi> aloud) Sir, the Lady is out o'dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being Flatter'd; and you may go on at the ſame rate, if you pleaſe. But (interrupted <hi>Philandra</hi>) you may aſſure your ſelf (my Lord) it will not altogether pleaſe <hi>me:</hi> And I cou'd wiſh, the Gentleman would ſpare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the trouble of a ſecond thought. At this they both bow'd very humbly,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99196:29"/>
and were ſilent: And (then ſaid the Lady <hi>Gripely</hi> taking up the Diſcourſe) but, in the name of Wonder, (Mr. <hi>Stopwell</hi>) how came you to find us here? Madam (reply'd the <hi>Coupé.</hi> Marchant) heaving that my Divine Miſtreſs was taken Sick upon her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to Town, I thought it my indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſible Duty to pay my Reſpects to her, in enquiring of her Health, if I might not have been permitted the Honour and Happineſs of ſeeing her; and this Afternoon I had the good Fortune to learn from Sir <hi>Beetlehead,</hi> then at home, that your Ladyſhips were gone towards the Park; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, as I was going to call a Coach, this worthy Gentleman, my Honour'd Friend prevented me, by taking me into his own Coach; he deſigning for a Walk in this place. While they were thus diſcourſing <hi>Worthygrace</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pen'd to fix his Eye on the Lady <hi>Arabella;</hi> where (perhaps) he diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cover'd as much Beauty and Goodneſs as ever was confin'd to one Perſon And (no doubt) he had thought ſo had he not been prepoſſeſs'd with
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99196:29"/>
a Paſſion for <hi>Philandra;</hi> however, at the ſame time, he cou'd not but be ſomewhat touch'd with <hi>Arabella;</hi> and was not a little ſurpriz'd to ſee two Perſons ſo exactly alike as the Lady <hi>Bellamant</hi> and <hi>Arabella.</hi> Mean while, on t'other ſide <hi>Bellamant</hi> taking <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra</hi>'s hand, and walking ſome few paces from the Company; ask'd her if ſhe knew that Gentleman, ſhe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, that this was the ſecond time ſhe had ever ſeen him; giving him an account withal of what had paſs'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em at their firſt ſight, the day before ſhe came to Town. Indeed (Madam, ſaid my Lord) he makes a very Graceful Figure, and ſpeaks well;—Pray Heav'n and you, Madam, it prove not to my diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: No; no (my Lord, ſaid <hi>Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi>) your Lordſhip does not conquer by halves.— I fear I have ſaid too much (added ſhe with a bluſh) but make the beſt and kindeſt uſe on't you can for both our Intereſts. Ah Madam (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd he, in a tranſport) you have almoſt taken away from me the power to thank you for this mighty Bleſſing,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:99196:30"/>
and to aſſure you, that I can have no Intereſt but what muſt Centre in yours.—But I don't like this ſame Dancing-Maſter; I fancy he helps to play the Game againſt me. No matter my Lord (ſaid ſhe) ſince I deal, you are ſafe.—But, come let us joyn Company; for the Lady your Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is at a loſs for us. Alas, my Memory! (cry'd <hi>Bellamant</hi>) I had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got till now to tell you, (Madam) that ſhe came with me hither particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to Kiſs your hands, e're ſhe goes to a Relation of ours who is a Lady Abbeſs in <hi>France;</hi> with whom ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns to ſtay near a Twelvemonth; beginning her journey about three days hence: By this time they were come up with the reſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, when <hi>Philandra</hi> told <hi>Arabella,</hi> that ſhe was ſorry to hear ſhe muſt all on a ſuddain loſe the happineſs of her Charming Converſation, which ſhe had as well promis'd to her ſelf, as wiſh'd to enjoy all the days of her life. Madam (reply'd <hi>Arabella</hi>) I have had ſo great a deſire of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome part of <hi>France</hi> theſe many
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:99196:30"/>
Years; that I cou'd no longer defer giving my ſelf that ſatisfaction: Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſince my Lady <hi>Abbeſs</hi> is now ſo preſſing in her Invitation: And, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs your Ladyſhip will lay your ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Commands on me to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; I muſt leave <hi>England</hi> within theſe few days: Ah Madam! (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd <hi>Philandra</hi>) I can pretend to no ſuch influence in your Ladyſhips Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Beſides, if I might, with <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> you may aſſure your ſelf, that, I wou'd rather wholly diſquiet my ſelf, than give the leaſt <hi>leaſt interruption</hi> to your Ladyſhips pleaſure. That were too great a Condeſcenſion in you, Madam, to me; (reply'd <hi>Arabella;</hi>) ſince you may be confident, that you have an Arbitrary and Diſpenſing power in every thing relating to my Brother. During this Diſcourſe between 'em, <hi>Worthygrace</hi> was examining the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of their Beauties; and found much more of Modeſty and Sweetneſs in <hi>Arabella</hi>'s Face, than Air and Gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, which did chiefly reſide in <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra</hi>'s; who yet had a Languiſhing caſt with her Eye at ſome times;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99196:31"/>
when ſhe deſign'd an Abſolute Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt; which did not a little denote her cunning: And 'twas this had van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh'd him more than the noiſe of her thirty thouſand pounds Portion: For he was truly Generous, and lov'd for loves ſake; and, that moſt paſſionately.—But now, remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Eyes from their belov'd object, and turning 'em on t'other ſide; he found the Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi> ſurveying him from Head to Foot: Which made <hi>Worthygrace</hi> as nicely examin him. At laſt, after a ſhort encountre of their Eyes:—Well, Sir (ſaid my Lord) what have you obſerv'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout me to my Advantage? I fear, nothing at all, (continu'd he) but what makes wholly for yours. So much on the contrary; (reply'd he) that I aſſure your Lordſhip, I wou'd not have you for a Rival of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: And I cou'd wiſh, with your Lordſhips Pardon, that you were not only <hi>like</hi> that Beautiful Lady (added he, bowing toward <hi>Arabella</hi>) in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Figure alone, but ev'n in her very Sex. I muſt avow to you, my
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:99196:31"/>
Lord, 'twou'd give me a great deal of eaſe. Methinks, Sir (ſaid <hi>Bella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant</hi>) you look on me <hi>already</hi> as one that is a Diſturber of your joys. If I do, my Lord, (return'd <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) you are too ſecure in your own Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to fear any attempt from me. As they were thus entertaining one another, Sir <hi>Blunder</hi> paſs'd 'em on one ſide of the Mall, cloſe to the Walk that leads to St. <hi>James</hi>'s Houſe, obſerving them moſt narrowly; but unobſerv'd of them. It ſeems, he was near enough to take notice that <hi>Bellamant</hi> led <hi>Philandra,</hi> and whiſper'd very frequently with her: That <hi>Step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> uſher'd the Lady <hi>Gripely;</hi> and <hi>Worthygrace,</hi> as yet a ſtranger to him, was fain to take up with the Fineſt Creature there: I mean, <hi>Arabella.</hi> What <hi>Bellamant</hi> and <hi>Philandra</hi> whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd ſeem'd to <hi>Slouch</hi> at that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to be ſome Aſſignation, or ſome Damn'd Love-Intrigue, or other, not at all in favour of him. An hundred times did he wiſh that he had been in my Lord's Heart; or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> leaſt, that he had had his Ears:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99196:32"/>
he durſt not venture to go near enough for either of 'em, for fear of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primand from <hi>Bellamant,</hi> who by this time was acquainted with the whole ſtory of his Villany: At laſt, all on a ſuddain, clapping her hand on her left ſide, <hi>Philandra</hi> miſs'd the Letter ſhe received from my Lord the day before. This made her ſtand as fix'd as the Statue at the end of the Canal: But in a more defenceleſs poſture. For, ſhe had already receiv'd a ſecond blow from Fortune; and there was no guarding her ſelf againſt what was paſt. By her looks on <hi>Bellamant,</hi> ſhe appear'd ſtrangely mortify'd at ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; which all the Company took notice of, upon that ſuddain motion of her's with her hand. Art not well, my Dear? (cry'd the Lady <hi>Gripely,</hi> running haſtily to her) yes, Madam (anſwered ſhe) pretty well now; I humbly thank your Ladiſhip. 'Twas only a ſtitch that took me on the ſuddain; and as quickly has left me. Ha! (thought <hi>Slouch,</hi> all this while watching ev'ry particular mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole Company; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:99196:32"/>
               <hi>Bellamant</hi>'s, and <hi>Philandra</hi>'s) I can tell your Diſtemper better than Mr. <hi>Phyſmacary</hi> himſelf: For I have the occaſion of it here in my Pocket, which I will ſo improve, that you ſhall either marry me, or dye of the Pip, and ſo lead Apes in Hell. I'm now go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your Father, and conſequently every ſtep I make is towards her Bad. Saying ſo, he left the <hi>Park,</hi> and them to follow him, which they did in leſs than an hour after, fearing the Air might be too ſharp for <hi>Philandra</hi>'s longer ſtay there the firſt time; every one expreſſing their real grief for the apprehenſion they had of the return of her Diſtemper. At the end of the <hi>Mall</hi> they were oblig'd to part; <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra</hi> and her Mother for the City, the Lady <hi>Arabella</hi> with her Attendant and one Footman return'd to their Lodgings in <hi>Soho-Square;</hi> for my Lord would needs take a Bottle with <hi>Worthygrace</hi> at the <hi>Blue-Poſts</hi> in the <hi>Hay-Market,</hi> where they did very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly with <hi>Stepwell,</hi> drinking to <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra</hi>'s Health, and diſcourſing of their Travels; in which, <hi>Worthygrace</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:99196:33"/>
had much the advantage, having ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome time in moſt of the Princes Courts in <hi>Europe. Bellamant</hi> having only made the Tour of <hi>France,</hi> and ſome ſhort ſtay at <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Venice.</hi> After which, he ſpent ſomewhat more than a Twelvemonth in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and the Campaign. Having drank and talk'd their heads pretty empty of further thought, and eaten their bellies full, they took a very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging farewell of each other, both extreamly ſatisfied with one anothers merit, but not a little diſſatisfied that they found they were Rivals; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, they Convers'd, and parted like Perſons of Honour, expecting from <hi>Philandra</hi> the fatal determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their happineſs, or miſery.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, as they were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king homewards, <hi>Philandra,</hi> looking very earneſtly on <hi>Mariana,</hi> ask'd her if ſhe had not met with a Letter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Linnen which ſhe had put off that day? To which ſhe reply'd, That indeed ſhe took up a Paper that lay on the ground, and becauſe ſhe could not read it, ſhe gave it to Sir
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:99196:33"/>
               <hi>Blunder,</hi> who told her that 'twas only a new Song which her Ladyſhip had tranſcrib'd; and that therefore ſhe took no farther notice of it, but left it with him. <hi>O thou Screcch-Owl,</hi> (cry'd Philandra, <hi>all in a flame) what do I hear? Oh! thou haſt betray'd me to the</hi> greateſt <hi>of misfortunes, expoſing me to the baſe practices of that Eternal Booby</hi> Slouch. <hi>O moſt unfortunate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident</hi> (cry'd the Mother) <hi>another Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter faln into his hands! Madam,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Mariana,</hi> about to juſtifie her ſelf.) <hi>Be dumb, be dumb for ever here on Earth,</hi> (interrupted <hi>Philandra) or if thou needs muſt yell, howl out inevitable Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Deſpairing Souls! Oh! It were Charity to what th'haſt done! what! Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crific'd a ſecond time to that Slave's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt? 'Twere mercileſs I'm ſure, in</hi> Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, <hi>to act thus, but</hi> Heaven <hi>I hope has kinder ends in it. Ah! Madam,</hi> (purſu'd ſhe) <hi>how ſhall we meet my jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Father, who is byaſs'd in every thing by that hated Fiend. No doubt</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd the Mother) <hi>the Greeting will be very extraordinary: Fools that we were</hi> (purſued ſhe) <hi>not to perceive 'till
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99196:34"/>
now, that this ſly Minks is a meer tool of his! his Creature; foiſted upon us, to ſerve his hated ends.</hi> All this while the plaguy Gypſy ſate ſobbing and blub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering, and ſtaining with her Crocodile tears her Handkerchief, which before was as white as innocence: At laſt, with much difficulty ſhe ſputter'd out, <hi>Madam, if your Ladyſhip thinks that I have deſignedly injur'd you in this, I humbly beg your Ladyſhip to diſmiſs me your Service, for I had rather be robb'd of that Happineſs and Honour, than live under your Ladyſhip's Diſpleaſure, and Suſpicion. Ah! wou'd to Heaven</hi> (cry'd Philandra) <hi>you had propos'd this ſome weeks ago, it might perhaps for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have eſtabliſh'd my Peace and Quiet, which now I fear is utterly ruin'd. However</hi> (continu'd ſhe) <hi>your Requeſt, tho' much with the lateſt, is very grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to me, and you may be confident you ſhall not be long without your wiſh, if my honour'd Mother has no further Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands for you Little did ſhe think that this diſmiſſion would be as wellcome to</hi> Mariana, <hi>as it was obliging to her: But I can aſſure you, it had been of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:99196:34"/>
equal advantage to all three, had it not been for a ſlippery Trick that Fortune play'd this unluckie Damſel.—No, no,</hi> (return'd the Lady <hi>Gripely) my laſt Command to her is, that ſhe continue in the Reſolution of leaving us, and that by to morrow this time.</hi> At theſe words they found themſelves juſt at their own door, which the Mother and Daughter enter'd, but with aking hearts, fore-boding but a ſorrowful reception, which was reſerv'd (it ſeems by the two ill-natur'd Block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads agreement) to a more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient time. For <hi>Slouch</hi> immediately upon his leaving the <hi>Park,</hi> came and found <hi>Gripeley</hi> at home, and took him to the Coffee-Houſe, where he recount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him all the Diſcourſe between the Mother and Daughter, as he had learn'd it from <hi>Mariana;</hi> ſhewing <hi>Bellamant</hi>'s Letter to <hi>Philandra;</hi> and withall, gave him an account of the Honourable Company he had ſeen with them in the <hi>Mall.</hi> He choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take him to a Coffee-Houſe, there to diſtract him with this Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than his own Houſe, fearing the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99196:35"/>
Ladies might return, and ſurprize him as he was doing 'em that ſignal piece of Knight's Service. The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies had juſt time to quit themſelves of that part of their Dreſs which was unneceſſary in the Houſe, when Old <hi>Gripely</hi> and <hi>Slouch</hi> came to 'em; the laſt of which (as it was contriv'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em, over a Cup of the Devil's Communion-Wine) after having paid his Reſpects to the Ladies, came up cloſer to <hi>Philandra,</hi> and taking the Letter out of his Pocket, convey'd it into her hand, as it were unperceiv'd of the Old Gentleman; who began to wellcome home his Lady Wife with all the Sugar-plum-words he us'd to feed her with at his firſt Courtſhip. This was ſurprizing, and kind; and, I am apt to believe, it was one of their laſt Honey-Nights: but for a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night after <hi>Philandra</hi> was under a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer reſtraint than ever; During all which time, ſhe could not receive one <hi>Billet-Doux</hi> from either my Lord, or <hi>Worthygrace,</hi> tho' they both had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to ſupply her a hundred times, and a hundred ways, with thoſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:99196:35"/>
Paper-Refections; eſpecially the Lord <hi>Bellamant:</hi> Who meeting <hi>Stepwell</hi> one Day about Noon, deſir'd him to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake one Bottle with him at the <hi>Roſe</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden:</hi> So to <hi>Long</hi>'s they came, where, after a Glaſs or two, <hi>Bellamant</hi> enquir'd of <hi>Worthygrace</hi>'s health, and drank to the continuance of it. Then he proceeded to ask <hi>Stepwell</hi> when he had been at Mr. <hi>Beetlehead,</hi> and how Matters went with <hi>Philandra,</hi> ſince they laſt ſaw her in the <hi>Park?</hi> Of which <hi>Stepwell</hi> could give him no further account, than that he underſtood ſhe was now more ſtrictly confin'd than ever. My Lord then taking him by the hand, preſented him with Fifty Guineas, and told him withall, that he muſt thence forward beg his Friendſhip; at the ſame time aſſuring him of his, and that he wou'd uſe his intereſt at Court, or any where elſe, to ſerve him at any time. To which he very obediently reply'd, <hi>That his Life, and all his Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, both Preſent, and Future, were, and ſhou'd be always at his Lordſhip's Devotion, except his Reputation, which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:99196:36"/>
he was confident my Lord wou'd never engage him to hazzard. Mr.</hi> Stepwell (ſaid the Lord <hi>Bellamant) had I thought that you had not had a true value for that, I ſhou'd not have ask'd your Friendſhip; and to ſhew you that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour I wou'd entreat of you is Juſt, and Honourable; I only deſire you to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to deliver this Letter to the hands of the Charming</hi> Philandra. <hi>My Lord</hi> (return'd he) <hi>that I will endeavour it, I do engage my Reputation to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and that within theſe two hours, for I am juſt going to Sir</hi> Beetleheads, <hi>to propoſe a Buſineſs that will be of no little advantage to him; but, that I ſhall ſucceed to your Lordſhips, and my own Wiſhes, I dare not promiſe. Your Endeavours are all I ask, Sir,</hi> (reply'd <hi>Bellamant) only this further I could wiſh, That you would let me know by to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row this time what ſucceſs you have had. Your Lordſhip ſhall find me moſt punctually and ſacredly Obedient in what you have Commanded me,</hi> (ſaid Stepwell.) <hi>I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doubt it, Sir,</hi> (return'd my Lord) <hi>tho' I am ſenſible that Honourable Friend of yours, has juſtly a greater intereſt in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:99196:36"/>
you than my ſelf: However, at the ſame time, I am aſſur'd you will oblige me in this, if he has not already engaged you to the contrary. Be confident, my Lord, he has not</hi> (reply'd t'other) <hi>only I beſeech your Lordſhip to let me</hi> know, <hi>if</hi> I may <hi>entruſt this Paper to any Perſon, who I am certain</hi> may <hi>and</hi> will <hi>preſent it to my Divine Miſtreſs her ſelf? By all means, uſe your own diſcretion in that</hi> (anſwer'd my Lord) <hi>for I wholly rely on your mannagement in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Thus, after having again con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated their Glaſſes with the Fair and Divine Lady's Health, and <hi>Step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> being well ſatisfied with the Fifty Guineas, as <hi>Bellamant</hi> was of his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity in this Affair; they parted; my Lord to the Court, and <hi>Stepwell to the Den of a Thief</hi>— I don't mean to Ch— tho', for all that; for he had had no buſineſs that way of a long ſeaſon; but to <hi>Gripeley</hi>'s he went, whither he got juſt at Dinner-time. There he deſir'd the Coachman-But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler-Porter to preſent his moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſervice to Sir <hi>Beetlehead;</hi> and withall, to let his Worſhip know,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:99196:37"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he had ſome Buſineſs of great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to diſcourſe him about, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he humbly beg'd the honour of ſome few minutes Converſation with him at his earlieſt leiſure. <hi>Reins</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd his Complement in the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Philandra,</hi> who from thence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to conceive ſome hopes of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Intrigue with <hi>Worthygrace</hi> at leaſt, or with ſome body or other by his means. The Old Jealous Knight had like to have forgot himſelf at firſt, and ſaid, deſire him to walk in; 'till looking on his Daughter, he cry'd out aloud in haſte, Sirrah, deſire him to walk into the outward Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, I will but diſpatch a bit or two, and then I'll come to him. <hi>Stepwell</hi> had not expected above a quarter of an hour, but <hi>Gripely</hi> came, and deſir'd him to ſpeak to the Buſineſs. <hi>Stepwell</hi> then told him, that an honour'd Friend of his, who had near Six Thouſand Pounds a year, was in a preſent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Four Thouſand Pounds; which, if he pleas'd to furniſh him with, the Gentleman his Friend wou'd Mortgage an Eſtate to <hi>Gripely,</hi> which
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99196:37"/>
he had in <hi>Glouceſter-ſhire,</hi> of Five Hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred Pounds a year, for his Security. Well, Mr. <hi>Stepwell (cry'd the Old hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Wolf</hi>) what is his Name? His Name I beſeech you, and where lies the reſt of his Eſtate? To which, <hi>(t'other reply'd)</hi> his Name, Sir, is <hi>Worthygrace,</hi> of the Ancient Family of the <hi>Worthygraces,</hi> Originally of <hi>York-ſhire;</hi> tho' the Family has ſpread it ſelf into moſt of the Counties of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Wales;</hi> ſome of the other parts of his Eſtate lay in ſuch, and ſuch, and ſuch Shires and Counties; giving him a more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular account than at preſent I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make you. Beſides, Sir, <hi>(ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he)</hi> I beſeech your Worſhip to take notice, that he is no Swearer, Whore Maſter, Drunkard, nor Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Piſh, piſh, <hi>(ſaid the other)</hi> 'tis not a pin matter to you, or me, whether he be or no; yet (perhaps) I cou'd wiſh he were all theſe: But ſince you ſay he is ſo fine a Gentleman, I pray you good Mr. <hi>Stepwell</hi> how comes he to have ſuch an urgent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for this Sum, or be obliged to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99196:38"/>
a Mortgage? Why, Sir, <hi>(reply'd Step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well)</hi> he is unwilling to expoſe his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to any of his Acquaintance, becauſe (poſſibly) he deſigns to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of their Daughters, wherefore he entreated me to aſſiſt him in this matter, ſince I have no knowledge of any of his Relations, or Country Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, more than your Worſhip has. Ay, but Mr. <hi>Stepwell (interrupted Gripely)</hi> you muſt give me leave Mr. <hi>Stepwell,</hi> you muſt give me leave to be better acquainted with him, and his Concerns, before I part with ſuch a Sum of mony to him; for it is my cuſtom ſo to do, it is indeed, Mr. <hi>Stepwell</hi>— Tho' I ſuppoſe <hi>(pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded he)</hi> this mony is to carry on his Deſign on the Lady. It is ſo, Sir, <hi>(anſwer'd the other)</hi> and he deſires by all means, that you wou'd give your ſelf the ſatisfaction of enquiring into the Circumſtances of his Eſtate, but at a diſtance, and with all poſſible caution, leſt his Reputation ſhou'd any way ſuffer. You may have a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Character of him, and certain Information of the poſture of his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:99196:38"/>
in <hi>York-ſhire, Glouceſter-ſhire,</hi> and <hi>Hertford ſhire,</hi> from any of the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Gentlemen of thoſe Counties. No, Mr. <hi>Stepwell (ſaid he)</hi> I ſhall not need I believe to give my ſelf any great trouble in this matter, if this be the Rich <hi>Worthygrace</hi> of <hi>York-ſhire.</hi> The very ſame, Sir, <hi>(ſaid Stepwell.)</hi> That's enough <hi>(Reply'd Gripeley)</hi> but tell me, Mr. <hi>Stepwell,</hi> is he already en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd to this Lady? Is ſhe a <hi>Beauty?</hi> Is ſhe a <hi>Wit?</hi> Or, what is chiefly to be conſider'd, is ſhe a Fortune? Sir, ſhe's worth ſome 15 or 16000 <hi>l. (Reply'd he.)</hi> That's but a ſmall Portion for ſo great an Eſtate as this <hi>(return'd Gripely)</hi> and, if he be not already <hi>too far Engag'd,</hi> I believe I can recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him to a young handſome Laſs, worth at leaſt Thirty Thouſand Pounds. On my word, Sir, <hi>(ſaid Stepwell)</hi> that wou'd be an extraordinary favour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and I fancy he has not made his approach ſo cloſe to her, but he can make an honourable retreat when he pleaſes. When may I ſee him then? <hi>(ask'd the Old Knight.)</hi> To morrow morning, if you pleaſe <hi>(reply'd t'other)</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:99196:39"/>
in the mean time, I will prepare him to receive your kindneſs with the greater readineſs, for (poſſibly) he will do ſomething this Night, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his diſengagement from the Lady he is now in purſuit of. Do ſo (<hi>ſaid Old</hi> Gripely) and let me ſee you both here to morrow at Eleven pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely. I ſhall, Sir, (<hi>Return'd</hi> Step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well) and took his leave.</p>
            <p>When he left Old Dry-bones, he went immediately to <hi>Worthygrace,</hi> whom he found at his Lodgings in <hi>Bloomsbury-Square,</hi> where he repeated every particular of his Diſcourſe with <hi>Gripely,</hi> to his honour'd Friend. Tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him withall, that it cou'd be no body elſe but <hi>Philandra,</hi> whom her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intended to propoſe for a Wife to <hi>Worthygrace;</hi> who was enclineable enough to believe it; and Rewarded the Care and Cunning he had ſhewn in the management of his Intereſt, with a Diamond Ring from off his finger, worth 40 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> which t'other receiv'd with as good a grace as any Coupé-Merchant in Town cou'd do. Sir, <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> your Preſent is of much
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:99196:39"/>
greater value than the Gold or Stone cou'd make it, forc'd from embracing your finger to adorn mine; which ſhall be no longer part of my hand, than it is able to ſerve you. Then <hi>Stepwell</hi> preſented him with the Lord <hi>Bellamant's</hi> Letter to <hi>Philandra;</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting him with the promiſe he had made my Lord, to deliver it to her own hands, or to ſome other Perſon who ſhould aſſuredly do it; nor did he conceal the 50 Guineas he received from <hi>Bellamant. Worthygrace</hi> was a little ſurpriz'd at that Letter, and at <hi>Stepwell</hi>'s Relation of their Rencoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and, tho' he had <hi>almoſt</hi> a <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Curioſity</hi> to ſee what it contain'd, yet he had too much honour to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify that fooliſh itch of his humour; and taking the Letter from <hi>Stepwell,</hi> You ſhall be as good as your word to my Lord, <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> for I will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it to her my ſelf, tho' never ſo much to my diſadvantage. I mean, if I have the happineſs to ſee her to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. You will not, I hope <hi>(cry'd Maître de Dance)</hi> be ſo far far acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to your own ruine there, as to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:99196:40"/>
attempt it. Pardon me, my Friend, (reply'd <hi>Worthygrace)</hi> but I will. I beſeech you then (ſaid <hi>Stepwell)</hi> read it firſt, Sir. Not for the purchaſe of my happineſs in <hi>her (return'd this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lover)</hi> I cou'd then never hope it, becauſe I'm ſure I ſhou'd not <hi>deſerve</hi> it. No, <hi>(continu'd he)</hi> invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late as it is, and teeming with all the moſt Beautiful and Charming Ideas, and Expreſſions of his paſſion that it may be; ſhe ſhall receive it from my hand the very firſt opportunity I have to offer it to her. Saying ſo, he wrap'd it up in a clean ſheet of Paper, and put it into his Scritore. At which (<hi>cry'd</hi> Stepwell) Forgive me, Sir, I beſeech you, if I think this the od<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt method of making Love for a Mans own ſelf, that I ever yet have heard of. Call it <hi>Knight-Errantry</hi> if thou wilt (<hi>return'd</hi> Worthygrace) but I have my ſatisfaction in it.—E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of this— To morrow by Ten in the morning, I expect you here. I ſhall then pay my duty to you, Sir, (ſaid <hi>Stepwell</hi>) and left him to give or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for the morrows Expedition;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:99196:40"/>
which he took care ſhould be as ſplendid as that little time would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</p>
            <p>At Ten the next morning <hi>Stepwell</hi> waited on him at his Lodgings, and ſoon after they made for Sir <hi>Beetle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi>'s; who, the preceeding Night told his Daughter, that now he hop'd he had provided her a Husband whom ſhe could no way except againſt: For <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> I have enquir'd of him of ſeveral Worthy Gentlemen, and Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Citizens, who all give me a moſt extraordinary Character of his Perſon, and Humour; and which is <hi>above all,</hi> of his Eſtate, being worth near Six Thouſand pounds <hi>per Annum.</hi> And now (my dear Girl) I prithee do not ſtand in thine own light: No force, <hi>(Good Sir ſaid ſhe)</hi> and I will ſtretch my Inclinations as far as may be, to embrace one of your choice, that I may reccommend my duty to you. Then he order'd her to appear as Gay and Glorious as ſhe cou'd, to receive him the next morning. Near a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before Eleven, <hi>Worthygrace</hi> got to Old <hi>Gripely</hi>'s, who entertain'd him very
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:99196:41"/>
Courteouſly, and Generouſly; calling for a <hi>whole</hi> Bottle of Canary, which he himſelf lov'd beſt, to drink to him. After which, the Devil's Caſheer, old <hi>Gripely</hi> (who only got and diſpos'd of his mony in the Devil's name, and for his uſe) fell upon the Buſineſs, and propos'd his Daughter to <hi>Worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace,</hi> with Thirty Thouſand Pounds, Who told him, that the Overture was, ſo much above his Merits and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, that he fear'd he did but motion ſuch great advantages on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to evade doing him that ſmaller obligation which he had entreated of him by Mr. <hi>Stepwell.</hi> Nor can I have reaſon, Sir, <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> to think other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſince I am yet abſolutely a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to you. I confeſs, Sir, (return'd <hi>Gripely</hi>) you was a <hi>Stranger</hi> to me 'till now; but your Circumſtances, I am, and have been before ſo well ſatisfied with, that I ſhall think both my ſelf, and Daughter moſt happy, if you will accept her for your Wife. But it is not fair to oblige you to a promiſe of that, before you have ſeen her; wherefore you ſhall each of you have
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:99196:41"/>
the ſatisfaction at the ſame time. We'll wait on you preſently <hi>(added he)</hi> and went to fetch her. Now, Sir, (ſaid <hi>Stepwell</hi>) will you take my word ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time? Did not I ſay 'twas his Daughter, my Divine Miſtreſs <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra,</hi> whom he wou'd propoſe to you? Ay, <hi>Philandra</hi>'s the Charm; (cry'd <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) his Daughter, and Thirty Thouſands Pounds were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe but dull muſick, but indifferent ſounds to me: <hi>Philandra!</hi> That <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra</hi> whom I firſt ſaw at the Board<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-School, whom I love!—No matter whoſe Daughter, or what For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune ſhe is, ſo ſhe may be my Wife. 'Tis the very ſame, Sir, I dare aſſure you (ſaid <hi>Coupé</hi>) Then for my Lord's Letter (ſaid <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) O! I have it with me, I find. After ſome little further Diſcourſe, <hi>Gripely</hi> led in the ſelf ſame <hi>Philandra</hi> to 'em, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd with her Mother. Here, Sir, (ſaid <hi>Gripely</hi>) Look you, this is my Daughter, as my Lady-Wife tells me, (and that was well put in) tell me how you like her, (pray?) Hah! you ſtand as if you were frighted at the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:99196:42"/>
ſight of her. I am amaz'd, Sir, (cry'd <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) at ſo much Beauty; and I beg the Lady will pardon the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, of which ſhe is the Cauſe. I proteſt that was ſpoken like your ſelf, Mr. <hi>Worthygrace (ſaid the Old Fool)</hi> like a fine Gentleman, and a Courtier: Nay, nay, I love to hear theſe Complements in an honeſt way—Perhaps 'tis not the Court faſhion to kiſs, or (it may be) you are aſham'd to do it before my face, therefore I'll be gone, and leave my Lady-Wife, and Daughter <hi>with you.</hi> No (Sir, reply'd <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) I dare do it in the face of <hi>Majeſty,</hi> of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf, ſince my thoughts are Juſt and Honourable. And I am ſorry, Sir, I gave you the occaſion of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing my duty. Saving ſo, he Saluted both the Lady-Mother, and Daughter. 'Uds precious <hi>(cry'd the Old Daddy)</hi> this puts me in mind of my wooing my Lady-Wife there; which I cannot remember without tears of joy: (And then (I think) he ſqueez'd as much moiſture out of his eyes, as might have made the tittle o're an j,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:99196:42"/>
had it been Ink. But <hi>(continued he)</hi> I'll leave you together, and ſhall expect to find you and Mr. <hi>Stepwell</hi> at dinner with me here to day. I have a little buſineſs—a little buſineſs, your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, Sir—Daughter <hi>(purſu'd he)</hi> this is the man for my money. With that (clapping <hi>Worthygrace</hi> on the ſhoulder, and going out) he eas'd 'em of a great deal of impertinence. I hope, Sir <hi>(ſaid the Lady-Mother)</hi> you'll pardon the infirmities of Old Age. And the defects of an Old Citizen's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation (added <hi>Philandra</hi>). It looks hearty and kind, Madam (return'd <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) and I cou'd wiſh, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, you wou'd receive me with as true a wellcome. Aſſure your ſelf, Sir, (reply'd <hi>Philandra</hi>) a Perſon of your merits can't want a due reception. We plead no merits from Heaven <hi>(return'd he)</hi> but (Madam) if ſelf-denyal, and other the greateſt mortifications be any way grateful, I am in hopes that this Preſent from me may give you a teſtimony of ſome of my weak Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours that way. And then he gave her the Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi>'s Letter. At laſt,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:99196:43"/>
(added he) I perſwade my ſelf I ſhall not fail of a welcome for his ſake that ſent it. She immediately knew the hand, and bluſh'd to receive it from <hi>Worthygrace.</hi> But recollecting her ſelf, <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> this I gueſs is ſome new piece of Gallantry from the Lord <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamant;</hi> which, howſoever, ſhall not rob me of the honour and ſatisfaction of your Converſation, Gentlemen. Nay, Madam (ſaid <hi>Stepwell,</hi> who all this while had been entertaining the Lady <hi>Gripely</hi>) we are but two to two, and, for my part, I decline any ſort of diſpute with your Ladyſhip. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, Madam (ſaid <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) rob not your ſelf of the pleaſure that Paper may afford you, for my ſake. For aſſure your ſelf, I had rather ſuffer all the anguiſh of deſpair and jealouſie, than you ſhou'd want the leaſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. Pardon me, Sir <hi>(return'd ſhe)</hi> this will ſerve to entertain me, when I want the advantge of better Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. Then, Madam <hi>(reply'd he)</hi> you muſt arm your ſelf to receive a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of much the ſame nature, I fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, with what that happy paper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:99196:43"/>
which will (undoubtedly) be more troubleſome to you, coming from me—I Love you, Madam <hi>(pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu'd he)</hi> with ſuch a paſſionate ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that I fear I cou'd <hi>almoſt</hi> part with you to my Rival; if it might ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance your happineſs—ſay, Madam, have you <hi>decree'd</hi> that I ſhall eternally be miſerable in your indifference; and have you <hi>determin'd</hi> that I muſt quit my pretenſions to my happy Rival? Blaſt, Madam, blaſt all my hopes with one cruel and irrevocable word, and let me dye by your Thunder. If, Sir, on me depends your happineſs, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, be confident I wiſh you the <hi>Firſt:</hi> And in a greater meaſure, than I can poſſibly create it to you. This indeed, Madam (ſaid <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) is an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging manner of <hi>Condemning</hi> me to the <hi>laſt,</hi> ſince you exclude me Paradiſe, and leave me all the <hi>lower</hi> World to range in—But be aſſur'd, Madam, <hi>That</hi> if all the Beauties of the Univerſe were divinely put together into <hi>One,</hi> by their Great Creator; <hi>That ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious One</hi> cou'd not bleſs me, were it not, as it is, <hi>your own Beauteous ſelf;</hi> who
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:99196:44"/>
will not receive me into thoſe joys you have entirely reſerv'd to the Lord <hi>Bellamant.</hi> Certainly, Sir, <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> this Tempeſt cannot be of long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance. This is ſuch a <hi>volley of</hi> Love as I <hi>never</hi> before received. Ah! Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, (cry'd he) you <hi>rally</hi> and <hi>play</hi> with my earneſt paſſion—Forgive me, if I ſay this is a little inhumane— But 'tis the effect of your Divinity that ſports it ſelf with my misfortunes. Doubtleſs (return'd <hi>Philandra</hi>) ſuch another ſtorm o' t'other ſide from my Lord, wou'd give me ſuch another ſurfeit, that I ſhou'd ſwoon at the very <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> ever after. Thus ſhe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded giving him any direct anſwer, either to make him hope, or deſpair; for ſhe thought 'twas convenient to keep him in play, leſt ſhe ſhou'd miſs of <hi>Bellamant.</hi> Their Conference laſted for near two hours, at the end of which, Old <hi>Gripely</hi> return'd.—Well, my new, but worthy acquaintance (ſaid he to <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs have you made in your Amours with my Daughter? Why, Sir, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd <hi>Philandra,</hi> (by way of queſtion)
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:99196:44"/>
D'you think the Gentleman is us'd to boaſt of a Lady's favours? Ah! Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam (cry'd <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) you have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken care that I ſhall have no ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion from you—But I can ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. 'Uds precious, Noble Mr. <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thygrace,</hi> (cry'd Old <hi>Gripely,</hi>) ſuffer me no ſuffers, I'll ha' no ſuffering here, unleſs it be, that I ſuffer you to make much of my Daughter, and that ſhe do the ſame by you—Come <hi>(con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he)</hi> Dinner wait's us in t'other room, and there we'll make much of our ſelves. 'Twas about two of the clock when they ſate down, and the laſt Courſe was ſerv'd in about Four, (for they had a Miſer's Feaſt) they all eat heartily, and were as pleaſant as their ſeveral Circumſtances would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit 'em.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi> having expected <hi>Stepwell</hi> 'till Three, who (you know) was otherwiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd, grew impatient, and on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain thought of a deſign not much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Worthygraces;</hi> commanded his Coach man to drive him to <hi>Gripely</hi>'s; where, juſt as he got out of his Coach,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:99196:45"/>
he found Sir <hi>Blunder</hi> enquiring for the aforeſaid Worſhipful <hi>Cent. per Cent.</hi> The Boobily Knight was ſtrangely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd to ſee my Lord at that place, and cou'd hardly Salute him, but with a malicious leer, and awkward bow. But my Lord knew how to make his advantage of ſuch an opportunity; and ſaid to him <hi>(returning the Compliment of Hat and Cringe,)</hi> that he was hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py to ſee him there, as well as to hear that Sir <hi>Beetlehead</hi> was at home: to whom, he deſir'd Sir <hi>Blunder</hi> to lead him the way. The Lubberly Booby had yet ſo much of pretended Good-manners, as to tell him he knew his duty better than ſo, and that it would be an honour to follow his Lordſhip. No <hi>(reply'd my Lord) Sans Façon</hi> good Sir <hi>Blunder,</hi> you are better acquainted here than I am, therefore pray take upon you for once the trouble of my Guide, and Leader. So in they went directly to the latter end of a Feaſt, which (perhaps) was the beginning of a Fray. But had not my Lord arriv'd juſt at that moment, when the Servant told Sir <hi>Blunder</hi> that <hi>Gripely</hi> was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99196:45"/>
he had certainly return'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edify'd as he came, as to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his Miſtreſſes Concerns— 'Uds precious (cry'd Sir <hi>Beetlehead</hi>) Sir <hi>Blunder,</hi> we have wanted you all this while to compleat our mirth, but you are now very wellcome—Ha, what fine Gentleman have you brought to my poor habitation? <hi>(purſu'd he, ſeeing my Lord)</hi> An humble Servant of yours, and of thoſe fair Ladies (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Bellamant</hi>) Mr. <hi>Worthygrace (ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he)</hi> we are happy to meet here. Ay, my Lord (return'd <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) we are ſo, in the ſight of theſe fair Ladies. 'Uds precious, my Lord, (cry'd Old <hi>Gripely</hi>) your Lordſhip is wellcome, if you don't bring a Pope in your Belly. No, Sir <hi>Beetlehead</hi> (reply'd <hi>Bellamant</hi>) but I brought an Angel in my heart, I mean your Daughter, Sir, who fills it with all the Ideas of Beauty that Humanity is capable of conceiving, and much more than it can expreſs. 'Uds precious, cry'd the Old man, (a little mellow) you are a fine Gentleman, my Lord, a fine Gentleman indeed; therefore
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:99196:46"/>
pray ſit down, or you'll tire me with ſtanding. I do ſo, Sir (ſaid my Lord ſitting) To make you eaſie, and to make my ſelf happy, I'll place me juſt oppoſite, and moſt remote to what I moſt love in this World, and to what you hate I ſhou'd make any nearer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to. Come, Sir <hi>Blunder (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd he)</hi> tho' you have been bleſt in the enjoyment of the pretty <hi>Marian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na;</hi> yet you are almoſt in the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances with me, as to the Beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Philandra.</hi> This, he ſaid, putting <hi>Slouch</hi> into the next chair to him. My Lord (ſaid <hi>Philandra,</hi> who thought it no more ſin to grieve the Spirit of the zealous Sir <hi>Blunder,</hi> than he did to lye with the Maid <hi>Marianna,</hi>) I fear your Lordſhip forgets that his Worſhip has been already ſo happy in his firſt Love, that he need not doubt his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs againſt another, eſpecially, when Aided, Abetted, Comforted and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by a Father's Good, Pious, and kind Inſtructions and Intentions; which yet he could not have want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but for your Lordſhip's and this Honourable Gentleman's Addreſs,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:99196:46"/>
and more plentiful Eſtates. But he may thank his Stars that there is one obſtacle remov'd, for it ſeems your Lordſhip is a Roman Catholick. And for my part, Sir <hi>Blunder</hi> (interrupted <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) I am ſo far from having receiv'd any particular favour from this our ador'd Lady, that I muſt ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſpair, unleſs her unparallel'd and matchleſs Duty prevail againſt her inclinations, and his Lordſhip's Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. Sir, (reply'd <hi>Bellamant</hi>) you have always the good <hi>Fortune</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> (it ſeems) to make me Debtor to your kind Opinion of me — wou'd to Heavens your <hi>Wiſhes</hi> were as much to my advantage. But, Sir <hi>Blunder (purſu'd he, changing the Diſcourſe)</hi> How does the poor Titt? Has ſhe yet taken her Degree in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> or <hi>Bridewell?</hi> It muſt be in the firſt; for certainly none but a mad thing wou'd ha' laid a miſcarriage upon an Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Fellow: It looks as if you had not been wicked, or able enough to get a Baſtard; when (no doubt) your <hi>Prentice</hi> might ha' done you that piece of ſervice, had you been Marry'd. But
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:99196:47"/>
ſince your Worſhip is a Batchelor, I ſuppoſe ſhe has been <hi>Flawg'd</hi> (as they call it) for putting the Saddle on the wrong Horſe's back—Ay, my Lord (return'd <hi>Slouch</hi>) the Wench did afterwards confeſs it was my Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice; for which (as your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſays) ſhe was <hi>Flawg'd</hi> in good faith. At which, they all laugh'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud: And (ſaid the Lady <hi>Gpipely</hi>) this is as happy and full a diſcovery as any Criminal cou'd make of himſelf. You're in the right, my Lady-Wife, (reply'd Old <hi>Gripely</hi>) 'twas a ſilly Wench, a ſilly Wench—But no more of that, if you pleaſe. No, (ſaid <hi>Bellamant</hi>) I muſt remind my ſelf of my Friend's buſineſs, about which I now come to ſollicit you. There is a Friend of mine <hi>(continu'd he)</hi> that wants five thouſand Guineas, now I can't ſpare him above two thouſand; wherefore, if you will oblige him, Sir, with that Sum, I will <hi>Engage,</hi> or <hi>Mortgage</hi> ſome port of my Eſtate for his payment of it Why, look you my Lord (cry'd <hi>Gripely</hi>) this <hi>Engaging</hi> muſt be <hi>Mortgaging,</hi> and I don't like
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:99196:47"/>
any of your Church-Lands. Hark you Sir <hi>Beetlehead</hi> (cry'd <hi>Bellamant</hi>) I fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that among all your Mortgages, you have one or more of our Church-Lands; that is, of Papiſts Church-Lands, as you ſtile 'em; and yet I find there is no great danger of their infecting you with Popery. But I mean ſome of thoſe Lands that my Lawful Father and Mother left to me (for perhaps ſhe was an Heireſs) thoſe will I dip unto thee. This requires farther thought, my Lord (ſaid he) and you ſhall have your anſwer to morrow this time. Nay, (reply'd <hi>Bellamant</hi>) if my my buſineſs, or my Friend's be not done by Six in the Morning, we ſhall have no further occaſion of yours, or any other aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Six a Clock is early (return'd the Old one) but I'll ſee what may be done, my Lord, after I have diſcours'd this Honourable Gentleman: So, my Lord, I beg your Pardon <hi>(continu'd he)</hi> taking <hi>Worthygrace</hi> out o'th' Room with him, to contrive the haſtening his Match with <hi>Philandra.</hi> 'Twas then <hi>Bellamant</hi> began to ſhew the violence
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:99196:48"/>
of his Love in his Jealouſie. Ah, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, ſaid he, approaching her, while the <hi>Coupé-Merchant,</hi> and the Booby Knight diverted the Lady-Mother; 'tis now high time for me to deſpair, ſince here I found my happy Rival; ſeated next to you, and feaſting on your Eyes; happy he is in every Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, in his Perſon, in his Sence, in his Eſtate, and, no doubt, happy in your Love. By your Father's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation encourag'd, receiv'd by you with a juſt opinion of his extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Qualifications; how long, <hi>Heaven</hi> knows, I'm ſure I know not— This he ſpoke ſomewhat low however, that they might not hear him; which they perceiving, were ſo civil as to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain each other with their own imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence. Nay, my Lord, ſaid <hi>Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> riſing, I find you are hot, we muſt walk. I thank you, Madam, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd he,</hi> that you ſeem at leaſt to take as much care of me, as my Grooms do of my Beaſts; tho' they never ran ſuch hot Courſes, as I do in purſuit of you. You flye me, Madam, now, <hi>continued he,</hi> you have ſhunn'd me
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:99196:48"/>
theſe fourteen or fifteen unaccountable days; for ſo they have been to me; ſince in all that time I have not once been bleſt with the ſight of you, 'till this hour. O Heavens! Madam, <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu'd he raving,</hi> where are all your vows? where are all your tender ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Love to me? Some indeed I wear about me, under your Hand and Seal; and all of 'em where you have fix'd 'em in my heart. Whence not you your ſelf can remove'em, unleſs you bid me deſpair, and dye—This is all wondrous fine, indeed my Lord, reply'd ſhe, and ſince I find you love me, even to Jealouſie, I'm reſolv'd to give your Lordſhip farther occaſions of that paſſion—And look you, my Lord, ſhe continu'd, I ſuppoſe I wear about me ſome of your Lordſhips tender expreſſions of Love in this Paper; which I receiv'd from your happy Rival, as you think him: This he deliver'd to me, un-open'd I dare believe—Unopen'd as it is! in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted he; now, by all my hopes on Earth, which terminate in you, Madam; my Love is not more ſacredly<pb n="86" facs="tcp:99196:49"/>
inviolate, than is this Paper; I know the Seal, and find 'tis not abus'd— Oh! this is more dreadful to me, than his pretenſions to you, Madam. And did he give it thus, without a ſcoff? Juſt as you ſee it, my Lord, and with reſpect (anſwer'd <hi>Philandra</hi>) Ah, wou'd h'had ſoften'd the hard faithful wax, and raviſh'd wide the innocent Contents! I then might juſtly have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd the wrong, and from his breaſt have torn a <hi>Villain</hi>'s heart, teeming with Sacriledge againſt you—But now, now it appears ſo Gloriouſly adorn'd, with your Bright Form in ev'ry corner of it, that I muſt fear to touch it. Oh, that Love ſhou'd rob me of ſo generous a Friend—I mean, whom I cou'd wiſh mine— Make him ſo, return'd ſhe, I ſhall not hinder ſuch a happy union. Nothing but you on Earth cou'd do it, Madam, reply'd <hi>Bellamant.</hi> Aſſure your ſelf I will not, ſaid ſhe—Here, my Lord, take your Letter, I beſeech you, and own the obligation he deſign'd you— 'twill be a good beginning of your Friendſhip—Now did this fair
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:99196:49"/>
Devil deſire nothing leſs.— No, Madam <hi>(replied he)</hi> I will not rob you of what <hi>He</hi> preſented to you: Beſides, if ever you had any regard of my Paſſion; I cou'd wiſh, you wou'd keep it: For, I fear, it is the laſt you will ever be troubled with from me. <hi>Troubled I wou'd have you,</hi> Madam, when you read it; to think how faithful and how Paſſionate a Lover you have thrown away. It ſeems my Lord (<hi>Return'd</hi> Philandra) you are at length grown <hi>weary</hi> of feigning a Paſſion; and wou'd now perſwade me, that I am diſpleas'd with your pretended ſervices: But, aſſure your ſelf, my Lord, Be it real or counterfeit; it has already given me a very pretty entertainment. You will e're long I doubt not, Madam, be judge of its truth or falſhood.— In the mean time, Madam; enjoy your ſelf, with the <hi>Thoughts</hi> of your new Lover! perhaps they will prove your only ſatisfaction. <hi>Philandra</hi> did not know what to make of this laſt part of his diſcourſe; and was about to beg his Lordſhip to explain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:99196:50"/>
juſt as her Father re-entred with <hi>Worthygrace.</hi> The chatt then was continu'd among 'em, for upwards of an hour; the Rivals plying their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs very warmly; who return'd their Volleys with equal heat: In which ſhe took accaſion to tell <hi>Worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace;</hi> that ſhe muſt have better proofs of his Love and Service, than a bare Tongue-Devotion: And, in order to that, he ſhou'd wave the advantage he had in her Father's opinion; and pay her no more Viſits, than he wou'd to an old, doating Relation of his, who liv'd moſt remote to him in Town; if any ſuch he had. To which <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thygrace</hi> reply'd, that he wou'd obey her, tho' to the hazard of his Life, and certain loſs of all his quiet. Madam <hi>(ſaid my Lord)</hi> if this worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Fate be ſo Rigorous; what ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity has your Ladyſhip reſerv'd for me! How often, I mean, how ſeldom may I be permitted to pay my Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to you in an Age? The ſeldomer the better <hi>(Return'd ſhe):</hi> once more will ſatisfie for your whole Life. So, (ſaid <hi>Bellamant</hi>) this comes of inquir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:99196:50"/>
into a Man's own deſtiny. Some farther prattle they had; at the end of which they took their leaves of the fair Ladys and the two Knights. As they were going out, my Lord told <hi>Worthygrace,</hi> that he had a Curioſity to ſhew him at his Lodgings; and therefore deſir'd, that he wou'd give him the favour of his Company thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Your Lordſhip (ſaid <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) ſhall Command me in any thing. But one; <hi>(Interrupted my Lord,)</hi> ſhewing <hi>Worthygrace</hi> into the Coach. Mr. <hi>Stepwell</hi> your Servant (<hi>ſaid</hi> Worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace) you had beſt make uſe of my Coach to your own Houſe. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieu, Mr. <hi>Stepwell</hi> (ſaid Bellamant.) He humbly made his Obeiſance to 'em both, and Roll'd home in State: But not without ſome ſuſpicion of what might happen betwen 'em.</p>
            <p>There were now no more in the Coach, than my Lord and <hi>Worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace;</hi> when my Lord, with a ſigh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan thus to him.—How ſtrangely does Fortune now at laſt begin to treat me! I mean, how ſeverely! ſince, 'tis the firſt moſt ſenſible Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:99196:51"/>
that ever touch'd me, to have <hi>you</hi> for my Rival. You, <hi>Worthygrace (continu'd he)</hi> whom, above all Men my Soul wou'd chuſe for its deareſt Companion in all things; but in a Miſtreſs. I know the greatneſs of your mind; have ſeen a little of the ſweetneſs of your Temper; have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd an obligation from you this day, in delivering my Letter to <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra,</hi> ſeal'd as I ſent it, by that <hi>Trifle Stepwell,</hi> from whom you had it. And, after all this, is it not hard, that I muſt own to you, I cannot be happy if you live? At leaſt in your pretenſions to <hi>Philandra!</hi> This, my Lord (reply'd <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the greateſt of my Misfortunes, ſince, (give me leave to own this ſacred truth to you!) your Lordſhip is the only Perſon among all Mankind, with whom I cou'd have contracted a moſt Religious Friendſhip: As, on the other ſide, That Charming Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, created to our Miſery, is ſhe alone in whom I <hi>muſt</hi> be happy, as in a Wife. O! Pardon me! (return'd <hi>Bellamant</hi>) you muſt not; while I live:
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:99196:51"/>
You muſt therefore force your happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs through me; as I will attempt mine from you. Tho' Heaven knows with what regret! To morrow, Sir, <hi>(continu'd he)</hi> I ſhall expect you on the backſide of <hi>Southampton</hi> Houſe. The Field is near your Lodging, and not far from mine. Bring with you, two of your beſt Friends, as I will of mine; whom I beſeech you engage to be no farther Active, than to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the eſcape of the ſurvivor. For, (haply) we may not both fall. Nor either of us, I cou'd wiſh (<hi>return'd</hi> Worthygrace) but (ah, my Lord!) theſe are but wiſhes. No more (ſaid <hi>Bellamant</hi>) but thus I have contriv'd it, if you pleaſe:—our Chairs ſhall wait us at convenient diſtance; and our Friends ſhall prevent the unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable kindneſs of our Servants. And now, in the mean time we'll pray for one another. And, if it be my Fate to fall by you; Heaven for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give you, in its ſweeteſt Mercy! And, if from you <hi>(my Lord)</hi> I meet my Death; Heav'n grant you happy life, here and hereafter; ſo <hi>Worthygrace</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:99196:52"/>
and ask'd, What hour, my Lord? 'Tis light enough at four (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd <hi>Bellamant</hi>) be that the hour: If 'tis befitting your convenience, Sir. I ſhall moſt punctually obſerve your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Commands, ſaid <hi>Worthygrace,</hi> Till then, let us embrace, and <hi>Think,</hi> and <hi>Act</hi> as Friends, <hi>(ſaid my Lord, embracing him)</hi> To which t'other return'd, and ſigh'd, ah! wou'd to Heav'n, my Lord, I might for ever thus claſp you, as my Soul's Heart!</p>
            <p>Having thus aſſign'd the time and place, they came at laſt to <hi>Bellamant</hi>'s Lodgings; where, after they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a friendly Bottle, <hi>Worthygrace</hi> left him, to find and prepare his Friends againſt the next Morning; which was as well <hi>Bellamant</hi>'s buſineſs that night. How ſoundly they ſlept I can't ſay: But they met exactly together at the time and place. Good morrow to your Lordſhip, (cry'd <hi>Worthygrace.</hi>) A happy one to my Dear and Honour'd Friend, <hi>(Return'd my Lord.)</hi> E're we begin this unfriendly diſpute <hi>(continu'd he)</hi> let me endeavour to make an acknowledgement and return of the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:99196:52"/>
Obligation you laid on me yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.—I here declare, before theſe Gentlemen, our worthy Friends, that I am the Aggreſſour: That I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd you to ſeek my Life, to defend your own. I know your Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with his Majeſty are not ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous for you, as I cou'd wiſh: I am ſenſible, you refus'd to ſerve him with your intereſt, for taking off the Penal Laws and Teſt. Mine are quite otherwiſe: This Letter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>purſu'd he,</hi> ſhewing a Letter, is ſuperſcrib'd <hi>To his moſt Sacred Majeſty,</hi> whom Heav'n bleſs! <hi>ſaid the Lord</hi> Bellamant; this of my Death will give a juſt account; as well as of the manner how I ſought it.—O! this, my Lord, reply'd <hi>Worthygrace, this</hi> is <hi>unjuſtly</hi> Generous: ſince 'tis Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val'd Love that makes us both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the moſt glorious prize. No more thy Friend but Rival think me then! cry'd <hi>Bellamant,</hi> as I will look on thee; our Swords will elſe want points. No <hi>more</hi> as Friend my Lord? sk'd <hi>Worthygrace.</hi> No more, <hi>t'other</hi> a <hi>reply'd. Philandra</hi> is the word: At
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:99196:53"/>
which they both drew; and fell to it <hi>heartily.</hi> Each was an excellent Maſter in that Bloody Science; and long was the diſpute: Many and large Wounds were dealt on both ſides; and the Effuſion of Blood was great on each part. At laſt they clos'd; and ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling, fell both together, with their Swords and Arms over each others back: And both endeavour'd to riſe, but neither cou'd: Which their Friends perceiving, each Party took his Man and bore him off to his Chair. But, to give 'em their due, thoſe Spectators wou'd fain have been <hi>other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe</hi> Active; and had been; had they not engag'd themſelves moſt Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to the contrary: And it was happy for the Principals, that they did not Act in the Bloody part of this Scene. So with Sighs and Tears almoſt guſhing from their Eyes, they took a ſorrowful leave of each other: And, going different ways, they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd of their Honourable unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Charges; as <hi>they</hi> over night had receiv'd inſtructions from them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:99196:53"/>The two Worthies were ſoon want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Friends and Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; eſpecially <hi>Worthygrace</hi> to <hi>Step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well;</hi> who, as I ſaid before, had ſome jealouſy of the deſign. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, next day he waited on <hi>Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra,</hi> to know, if ſhe had ſeen, or heard from him: Who was a little ſurpriz'd, to hear him enquire of his Friend from <hi>her.</hi> I was going, Mr. <hi>Stepwell, ſaid ſhe,</hi> to ask you concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his health. His Health, Madam! <hi>(reply'd he in a melancholly tone)</hi> pray Heaven, he has his life! What means this? <hi>ask'd ſhe.</hi> I'll ſay Amen to that Prayer always. But ſatisfie me, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, why is there a more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular neceſſity of it <hi>now?</hi> He then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted her with the Grounds he had for his Suſpicion, that <hi>Bellamant</hi> and he had fought. Avert it Heaven! <hi>ſaid ſhe.</hi> She had hardly made an end of this ſhort Petition; e're her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother came in trembling. The firſt, in a doleful hey (perhaps, in <hi>gam-ut</hi> or <hi>C-fa-ut</hi> flat. In which moſt of our famous farewells are ſet,) told her, that the Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:99196:54"/>
had baſely Murther'd Noble Mr. <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thygrace.</hi> However, <hi>added he,</hi> 'tis ſome comfort yet, that he firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd that Papiſt Bully; who elſe wou'd ha' Cut his Throat, with Piſtols, Fuzees, Musquet, Blunderbuſſes, and all ſorts of Fire-Arms. At this <hi>Step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> cou'd hardly forbear ſmiling, for all this ſorrowful account of his Friend and Patron: But <hi>Philandra</hi> and her Mother were almoſt drown'd in floods of their own Tears. Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>Philandra,</hi> recollecting her ſelf a little, told her Father, that ſhe cou'd not believe, <hi>Bellamant</hi> had <hi>baſely</hi> Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd <hi>Worthygrace;</hi> ſince he himſelf was kill'd before. No, no, Madam, reply'd <hi>Stepwell,</hi> all the World knew my Lord too Generous to do any thing below the Character of the braveſt. But, why, Mr. <hi>Stepwell, ſaid the Mother,</hi> ſince you had but too juſt a ſuſpicion of their intention; why did you not endeavour to prevent 'em in it? Alas, Madam, <hi>reply'd he,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Heaven or the King's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands cou'd have hinder'd it. Nor cou'd the laſt have <hi>long</hi> obſtructed
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:99196:54"/>
their fatal Reſolutions. O, moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate of Womankind! cry'd out <hi>Philandra:</hi> Who will endure to hear my hated name? Since, for <hi>my</hi> ſake two ſuch brave Men are loſt. My dear Daughter, and only Child <hi>(ſaid the old Man)</hi> do not grieve ſo immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately! Sir <hi>Blunder</hi> is yet alive, who will make a better Husband for <hi>thee</hi> than either of 'em; and him, I reſolve thou ſhalt marry to morrow; or I profeſs, thou ſha't not inherit one hundred pence of my Eſtate. At this the Daughter fell into a ſwoon, and no ſooner was ſhe come to her ſelf, than the Lady-Mother fell into a Fit: Inſomuch, that there was a moſt hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſtink for the ſpace of an hour and half: In all which time ſhe ſhew'd variety of Poſtures, and wonderful A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gility of Body. The Perfumes with which they entertain'd her dainty Noſtrils, were <hi>Aſſa Foetida,</hi> Spirit of <hi>Armoniac</hi> Salt, Spirit of <hi>Caſtor,</hi> Oil of <hi>Amber:</hi> The next Fumigations were of abount a pound or two of Feathers, and a blue Apron and half of the Kitchin-Maids; which laſt ſtank ſo powerfully, that it brought
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:99196:55"/>
her a little to her ſelf!—Give me a little Water <hi>(Cry'd ſhe in a weak Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing tone)</hi> at which her then uſeful Husband ſaluted her on one ſide, with the wholeſome Scent of Spirit of Harts-horn; which, with a Cup of Flower and Water did her buſineſs moſt effectually for the preſent: Tho, when Mr. <hi>Phyſmacary</hi> came to look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her caſe; he pronounc'd her a Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Woman. For ſhe had ſo ſtrain'd her ſelf in acting her part, that there was not a joynt about her, that did not moſt ſenſibly ſuffer in this elaborate Scene. Beſides ſhe had been too frequently buſy in her Cloſet, with her cold Tea and right Iriſh Uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebagh; ſo that in leſs than a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nights time ſhe dy'd: And not many days after, the old Skeleton her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band cheated the Worms with a meer dry Carkaſs. However he had the ſatisfaction e're he dy'd, to ſee and ſpeak with his dear Daughter; to whom he gave the bleſſing of above 30000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> Eſtate. For the other Bleſſing of his Prayers ('tis fear'd) they did her more hurt than good. <hi>Philandra,</hi> during the time of his ſickneſs, was
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:99196:55"/>
very diligent in her Attendance on him; which he rewarded with all his Worldly goods, except a thouſand pounds; which he bequeath'd in Legacies to ſome of his Piteous Poor near Relations, and to his menial Servants. Not forgetting his good Friend Sir <hi>Blunder;</hi> to whom he gave a Diamond-Ring worth above an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds; and withal begg'd his kind aſſiſtance of his Daughter, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhe ſhou'd need it: Recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to her once more as the fitteſt Man for her Husband.—You may believe, ſhe took on like any <hi>thing,</hi> for the death of a Father, whoſe life robb'd her of ſuch an Eſtate; and the Pleaſure of managing it according to the Gayety of her humour.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing ſhe did then, after the Interrment of her Father, which was very ſolemn and ſumptuous, was to remove from that diſmal Scene of Sorrow and Villany; that damn'd, ugly, old, dark Houſe in the City, whence ſhe had bury'd her two beſt Friends; to <hi>adorn</hi> a Country-Houſe of her's about ſeven miles off; where ſhe continu'd, to every one's thinking that
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:99196:56"/>
ſaw her, in deep Mourning ſomewhat more than a month: In which time the two Rivals were perfectly cur'd of the Wounds they had given each other, by the extraordinary care and skill of their Friends, on both ſides; which however was unknown to each other. But the Wounds they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd from their falſe and Cruel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs (as <hi>Bellamant</hi> and <hi>Worthygrace</hi> both thought her) were ſtill bleeding freſh, if any body cou'd have ſeen into their <hi>Hearts,</hi> you muſt think. The news of their Death was ſtill currant all over <hi>England,</hi> among thoſe who had heard of their diſpute; as well Friends as Strangers: unleſs, among thoſe who manag'd this report: which gave <hi>Worthygrace</hi> opportunity to ſlip over into <hi>France,</hi> in a diſguiſe; where he thought to find a Brother of his, of about ſeventeen: But (it ſeems) he was gone for <hi>Rome</hi> about 2 months before the arrival of his elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Mean while the Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi> caus'd a Coffin to be privately bury'd in a Chappel of his in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> where beſt part of his Eſtate lay: The Report of his Death, which
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:99196:56"/>
now was no longer doubted, gave him the happy opportunity of Transforming himſelf into the habit of his Siſter <hi>Arabella;</hi> the exact like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he had before; inſomuch, that he might eaſily have deceiv'd his own Wife, if he had been marry'd, unleſs, perhaps, in Bed.</p>
            <p>'Twas in this ſeeming Tranſmuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sexes that he waited on <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra</hi> at her Houſe (for he had an account of all her motions, as well as of all the accidents in the Family at the old Dungeon) The counterfeited <hi>Arabella</hi> pretended to be iuſt arriv'd from <hi>France,</hi> and that ſhe came to enquire of <hi>Philandra,</hi> whether my Lord her Brother were alive or dead. <hi>Philandra</hi> was ſtrangely ſurpriz'd to hear that <hi>Arabella</hi> was come to give her a viſit; and ran inſtantly, with all the wings that wonder cou'd give her; and add to thoſe, the haſte that her love to the memory of the Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi> inſpir'd her with, and you can think no otherwiſe than that ſhe <hi>flew</hi> to receive the ſuppos'd <hi>Arabella,</hi> whom ſhe embrac'd with the moſt endearing expreſſions of Love, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:99196:57"/>
Friendſhip, that a Soul like hers was capable of pretending; adding a kiſs almoſt at every period. And when ſhe nam'd <hi>Bellamant,</hi> whole Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of tears flow'd ſilently from her fatal, and then moſt charming eyes; as if ſhe ſeem'd to endeavour with thoſe, to waſh off her guilt of his blood. <hi>Bellamant</hi> was damnably put to't, to check and withold himſelf from a diſcovery of who he was; ſo provoking were her Careſſes: But the apprehenſions he had of his Rival's death, forbad him to hazar'd his life in a Womans hands, tho' it had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt flown from him whether he wou'd or no, while ſhe was kiſſing him. With ſome difficulty I think he got looſe from the Serpent's em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces; telling her, that the memory of the dear Lord her Brother was ſo afflicting, that unleſs ſhe took a little air, ſhe ſhou'd immediately Die away. With that, he withdrew to the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and a kind freſh gale pretty well cool'd him. Then turning again to her, he preſented her with a Paper. See here, Madam <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> how paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately and conſtantly my dear Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:99196:57"/>
lov'd you; this I found among ſome Papers of his, ſuperſcrib'd to you. <hi>Philandra</hi> took it, and read,
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>At length Diſdain</l>
                     <l>Has broke the Chain,</l>
                     <l>And I am no longer your Amorous Slave;</l>
                     <l>My heart is too great,</l>
                     <l>For ſo ſervile a Fate,</l>
                     <l>And meerly Deſpair now has render'd me brave.</l>
                     <l>With equal contempt I behold all your Frowns,</l>
                     <l>And defie all the ſcorn which on me you miſplace;</l>
                     <l>For (alas) 'twas my madneſs that gave my Wounds,</l>
                     <l>And all my Devotion, Idolatry was.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But (Oh!) my heart,</l>
                     <l>Still feels the ſmart,</l>
                     <l>And Death, I perceive, will the Conqueſt compleat;</l>
                     <l>Then frown once again,</l>
                     <l>T'encourage my pain,</l>
                     <l>And let not your Pity, your Rigour defeat:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="104" facs="tcp:99196:58"/>For ſince I muſt fall a Martyr to Love,</l>
                     <l>Let e'ry ſad Circumſtance torture my breaſt;</l>
                     <l>That I your Injuſtice the greater may prove,</l>
                     <l>And you be Tormented, when I am at Reſt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This, Madam, ſaid he, you may believe was written ſince his fatal en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement with Mr. <hi>Worthygrace;</hi> for the Characters of the Letters ſeem, as if made by a weak and tremulous hand. I fear they were, reply'd ſhe, but his Character is engrav'd here in my heart, too fair and deep to be eraz'd by any thing but Death. The feign'd <hi>Arabella</hi> then gave her his Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture drawn in minature, and ſet in Gold, incircled with Diamonds, and other Stones of great value; which ſhe receiv'd with a thouſand kiſſes, and lodg'd it between her lovely Breaſts. That, Madam, ſaid he, ſhould have been the Throne of the Living and Subſtantial <hi>Bellamant.</hi> And
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:99196:58"/>
ſo it ſhou'd, return'd <hi>Philandra,</hi> cou'd he but live again. In vain we wiſh, or ſuppoſe that, Madam, reply'd he, I muſt therefore divorce my ſelf from your dear ſight, that with the greater freedom I may alone mourn his hard Fate. 'Twill be perform'd with the greater Solemnity, Madam, (ſaid <hi>Philandra</hi>) if you ſtay, and ſee me bear the heavier part; for the loſs of a Brother is not comparable to that of a Lover. However, Madam, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd he, I ſhall be the more ſenſibly afflicted, to ſee my ſelf out-done in my Grief. No, Madam, interrupted <hi>Philandra,</hi> you ſhall not rob me ſo ſoon of your Charming Converſation, for I did at leaſt flatter my ſelf with the hopes of your Ladyſhips ſtay here this week. You'll pardon me, Madam, ſaid <hi>Bellamant,</hi> I have yet lain but two Nights in <hi>England,</hi> and have not ſo much as any outward ſhew of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the loſs of ſo dear a Brother. As ſoon as I reach'd the Town, I went to pay my earlieſt reſpects to you, Madam, at the old Houſe; and not finding you there, I learn'd from
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:99196:59"/>
Sir <hi>Blunder</hi> where I might be ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. And now, Madam, <hi>added he,</hi> you cannot but grant that it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary I ſhou'd make all poſſible haſte to my dear Brother's Lodgings (whence I came directly to wait on you) to order what befits my Quality, and preſent Circumſtances. In this, (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd <hi>Philandra</hi>) tho' with ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret, I muſt ſubmit to your Ladyſhip, yet not without a promiſe of as ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a return as your Honours conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience ſhall preſent. I do moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly oblige my ſelf to that happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Madam, <hi>Reply'd the Beautiful Counterfeit,</hi> and I am ſo far provided, that I have already found, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd my Brother's Coach-man, and two of his Footmen, who brought, and attended me hither; but <hi>Theodora</hi> my Woman, whom I took with me to <hi>Paris,</hi> I left there at my coming away, hardly recover'd of a Surfeit ſhe took with eating too many Grapes: Nor do I mean to take any other, being almoſt aſſur'd of her Recovery. Secure in your goodneſs of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, Madam, ſaid <hi>Philandra,</hi> I ſhall
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:99196:59"/>
now more earneſtly look and wiſh for that kind and bleſſed day, that ſhall return you to my longing arms, than I ſhou'd expect my Wedding-day with the moſt Beautiful and moſt Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd Man breathing. O happy, yet happy <hi>Bellamant</hi> (cry'd he) if thou knewſt how kindly thou art preſerv'd in her memory, to which, I eternally recommend, and leave him. Madam (return'd <hi>Philandra</hi>) I am your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours moſt humble Servant— So waiting on him to his Coach, they bowed, and parted.</p>
            <p>While <hi>Bellamant</hi> was thus ſucceſsful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſonating his Siſter <hi>Arabella; Worthygrace,</hi> who had been near a fortnight in <hi>Paris,</hi> one day made a viſit to a Lady of Quality of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer acquaintance; with whom he found the Lady <hi>Arabella,</hi> in company with the Lady her Relation, to whom ſhe went over. You may imagine he was a little ſtartl'd at ſo ſtrange a Rencounter, eſpecially, when her Beautiful Face reminded him ſo nearly of the Lord her Brother, whom he believ'd kill'd by his hand. He was
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:99196:60"/>
going therefore to retreat; telling the Lady, that ſince he ſaw her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in better Company, and, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in greater buſineſs than a bare formal Viſit, which he then came to pay her, he wou'd take an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to wait on her, to obtain his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, for having given her a diverſion of happineſs ſhe muſt needs enjoy in the Converſation of thoſe fair La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
            <p>The Lady, his friend, who was of an extraordinary good humour, and had a great reſpect for him; ran im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to him, and taking him by the hand, told him, that his viſit was ſo ſurprizingly pleaſant, ſince ſhe had not ſeen him in more than a twelve month, and knew not that he was in <hi>France;</hi> that if Madam <hi>Maintenon</hi> had been there, diſcourſing and conſulting her how to make her great at Court, (which ſhe cou'd not be ſo vain or fond as to wiſh) ſhe wou'd certainly have left her abruptly, to have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd of his health, and the preſent ſtate of his Affairs, if he wou'd not have condeſcended to joyn converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:99196:60"/>
with them. <hi>Worthygrace</hi> ſeeing himſelf ſo finely drawn in, ſet as good a face upon the matter, as his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience wou'd permit him; and after having made his <hi>Baiſe-mains</hi> to all three of them, he ſat down, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd 'em very pleaſantly for about half an hour; partly with ſome of the late accidents that befell him in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> giving 'em a little hint of the paſſion he had for a Beautiful Lady; but never ſo much as touching upon any diſpute he had for her, or naming the Lord <hi>Bellamant. Arabella,</hi> who all this while look'd on him very ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when ever his eyes were turn'd from her, which he took care ſhou'd not be very often. Told him, after he had given 'em an account of his misfortune in Love, ſhe fancy'd ſhe had the honour to be known to that Beautiful Engliſh Lady, to whom he had pay'd ſo great a devotion, as well as the good fortune to have ſeen him once in the <hi>Mall</hi> with her, where then was the Lord <hi>Bellamant,</hi> her Brother. And I remember, Madam, return'd he, that I then had the happineſs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:99196:61"/>
thoſe irreſiſtable Charms you bear about you, without the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of any danger from 'em; ſince then I was pre-poſſeſs'd: But now I find a greater misfortune attends me; for that I know, from this moment I muſt both Love, and Deſpair. <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella,</hi> who poſſibly had a very advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous opinion of his Perſon, and Character, the laſt of which, ſhe had from her Brother; bluſh'd, and ſmil'd, telling him, that ſhe cou'd not but commend his Gallantry, tho' it were ſo cuſtomary to him. She then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to ask him when he ſaw her Brother? and whether he were well, or no? To which, he anſwer'd, that it was near two months ſince he had the honour to ſee him. And, added he, Madam, I hope <hi>in Heaven</hi> he is well. If, Sir, ſaid the Lady <hi>Arabella,</hi> you have had ſuch ill fortune in your Love of <hi>Philandra,</hi> I am apt to flatter my ſelf, that my Brother may have better; ſince I have often heard him ſay, he valu'd no Rival but your ſelf. I can aſſure your Ladyſhip, reply'd he, he has none of me <hi>now.</hi> But when
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:99196:61"/>
did your Ladyſhip hear from him? Not theſe two months, return'd <hi>Arabella,</hi> that is, Sir, I have receiv'd but one Letter from him ſince I left <hi>England;</hi> which came to me ſome few days after my arrival hither—<hi>Worthygrace</hi> thought it was very odd, that he ſhou'd have been almoſt as long dead, and ſhe not have an account of it in all this time. However, he thought fit to ask her no more queſtions for Conſcience ſake. So that after about an hours more diſcourſe of the Affairs of the <hi>French</hi> Court, and of Things indifferent to them, the Ladies took their leave; and when <hi>Worthygraee</hi> had ſeen 'em in their Coach, he return'd with his good humour'd Acquaintance; to whom he made a ſolemn declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his ſudden paſſion for <hi>Arabella;</hi> and withall, told her what reaſon he had to deſpair of ſucceeding in it; not ſo much as omitting the Duel, nor the fatal Conſequence, <hi>as he thought, of it.</hi> The Lady was much diſturb'd at the bloody part of the ſtory; however, ſhe promis'd her aſſiſtance, and the intereſt ſhe had
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:99196:62"/>
with the Perſon of Honour, <hi>Arabella</hi>'s Relation. But by the way, ſhe ask'd him, how he cou'd ſo eaſily quit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of <hi>Philandra</hi>'s Chains, and ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately fall paſſionately in love with <hi>Arabella?</hi> To which he reply'd, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, your laſt Queſtion is an anſwer to your firſt, becauſe I am faln paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately in love with <hi>Arabella,</hi> whom at firſt ſight I thought one of the moſt Beautiful Creatures in the world; therefore I have quitted my ſelf of <hi>Philandra</hi>'s chains. Nor is this all, for I am ſenſible, that this Lady was Educated in all the ſtrict, yet ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Principles of true Vertue, and Honour, tho' ſhe be a Roman-Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick: Not to ſpeak of the advantage ſhe has of <hi>Philandra,</hi> in real Beauty; which, on a review, any impartial eye may diſcern; when t'other has but a tawdry, wanton, fading pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs, which cannot hold above ten years. Nor will I much reflect on the ill Principles of her Parents, nor the Ill-gotten Eſtate, that made her Father the firſt <hi>Worſhipful</hi> Rogue of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; who brought her up in the true
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:99196:62"/>
Whining and Canting Principles of a moſt Famous City, where there are above a thouſand ſeveral Families of the <hi>Gripley</hi>'s. But why, ask'd the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, was not all this conſider'd before you fought? Before we fought, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, reply'd he, I lov'd her, and cou'd think o' nothing but enjoying her. But, Madam, continued he, to your diſcretion I commend all my fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture happineſs on Earth; and I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly kiſs your hands 'till to morrow. Be confident, ſhe return'd, you ſhall not want the beſt endeavours of your Servant.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Worthygrace</hi> left her, he went directly to his Lodgings, and diſpatched a Letter to his Siſter <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietta,</hi> a Lady of about Eighteen; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a year older than her Brother <hi>Horatio,</hi> at that time in <hi>Italy:</hi> In which, he entreated her by all means, to confirm, and continue the Report of his Death; and with all, begg'd of her to diſpence with her modeſty ſo far for his ſake, as to perſonate her younger Brother in Man's habit; for in that borrow'd ſhape, ſhe might the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:99196:63"/>
more freely converſe with Gentlemen in Town, ſome of which, might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily give her a certain account, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi> were living, or dead; if not, poſſibly <hi>Philandra</hi> wou'd, whom he adviſed to deceive with that diſguiſe, unleſs ſhe found her a friend to his intereſt; which wou'd undoubtedly ſtrengthen her, and all the reſt of his Acquaintance, in the opinion of his death, and that perhaps, was the only way to preſerve his life. With this Letter, he ſent her a Bill of Exchange for a Thouſand Pounds, that ſhe might appear as her Brother <hi>Horatio,</hi> next Heir to the Eſtate.</p>
            <p>Upon peruſal of theſe Papers, ſhe was at firſt in a diſpute, whether ſhe ſhou'd act according to her Brother's entreaty, or obey the ſevere dictates of her modeſty, which ſeem'd abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely to forbid her to change her Sexes habit: but at laſt ſhe was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rul'd, by the neceſſity of her Brother's Circumſtances. Wherefore leaving <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> in Man's Cloaths, with a young Gentlewoman her Attendant,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:99196:63"/>
ſhe came to Town; where ſhe equip'd her ſelf, and her Companion with Mourning Suits; the Mourning Coach and Liveries were ſoon prepar'd, and all things neceſſary, and decent. And thus accouter'd, ſhe reſolv'd firſt for <hi>Philandra</hi>'s, having had a great cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity a long time, to ſee that fatally Celebrated Beauty. Rightly imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning too, that ſhe might as ſoon learn the certainty of <hi>Bellamant</hi>'s Life, or Death, from her, as from any one of my Lord's Acquaintance in Town, to whom ſhe was as yet a ſtranger. The feign'd <hi>Horatio</hi> was moſt kindly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by <hi>Philandra,</hi> with all the ſigns of a moſt ſenſible grief, for the death of ſo brave a Man, and ſo Generous a Lover as <hi>Worthygrace.</hi> Telling the Counterfeit <hi>Horatio,</hi> that ſhe cou'd not part with ſo near a Relation, and ſo dear a Friend of that Worthy Man, whoſe Love was his only fault, and misfortune; without giving him more ſignal proofs, and ample expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the veneration ſhe had for his Memory; wherefore ſhe muſt needs oblige him, and his friend, to ſtay
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:99196:64"/>
ſome few days with her; which, after ſome importunity, they yielded to; where we will leave 'em, and make a trip over into <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next day after <hi>Worthygrace</hi> had entertain'd <hi>Arabella</hi> with the diſcourſe of his unfortunate Love; the <hi>French</hi> Lady of Quality, <hi>Worthygrace's</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Friend, went with him in his Coach, to wait on the Lady <hi>Arabella,</hi> whom they found almoſt drown'd in tears; however, ſhe receiv'd 'em with all the evenneſs of temper that her afflicted Circumſtances wou'd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of. The Lady ask'd her, what cou'd ſo ſuddainly overcaſt the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtom'd Sun-ſhine of her face, and ſerenity of her mind; with which but yeſterday ſhe had made 'em ſo happy. She reply'd, that ſhe had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd a Letter not two hours ſince, that brought her a certain account, that her Brother was kill'd in a Duel, about two months ago.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, Madam, <hi>(purſu'd ſhe)</hi> I hope, you'll rather pity and pardon, than blame theſe Tears; which ſeem to give your Ladyſhip and this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:99196:64"/>
Perſon, your Friend, but a rude and untoward Reception. Ah, Madam, <hi>(reply'd the French Lady with Tears in her Eyes)</hi> your Grief appears ſo beautiful and juſt on ſo ſad an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion; that I'm in Love with it; and muſt, in ſome meaſure partake of it. For, I have ſometimes had the Honour of my Lord your Brothers obliging Converſation.—All this <hi>(you may believe)</hi> was no little mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to <hi>Worthygrace;</hi> who told <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella,</hi> that, tho' Nature had deny'd him the relief of expreſſing his ſorrow in Tears; yet he believ'd, his Heart was as ſenſibly touch'd with the loſs of ſo Gallant a Man, even as the Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Arabella</hi>'s. <hi>(And I am apt to Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit him)</hi> And, Madam, <hi>(continu'd he)</hi> ſince we find your Ladyſhip under ſo great a preſſure of Affliction we ought to eſteem our ſelves happy in our viſit to you; ſince we may help to bear ſome part of its weight, and break the violence of its fall on ſo tender a Heart. In my opinion <hi>(ſaid</hi> Climane, <hi>the French Lady his Friend)</hi> 'twere bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, we let the torrent of her Grief
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:99196:65"/>
waſte its impetuoſity without any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; and leave her, as it were to <hi>Enjoy</hi> the fullen Uſurper of her Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. There is a kind of ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in a ſilent and interrupted Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly. 'Tis confeſs'd, Madam, <hi>(re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd he)</hi> but to give place to it at firſt I fear, may embolden and confirm it. I am oblig'd, Sir, (ſaid <hi>Arabella</hi>) to the kindneſs of your fears: But, I muſt needs acknowledge it a greater Obligation, if you will permit me the Pleaſure of this one days retreat. For theſe enſuing hours (return'd <hi>Climane</hi>) we ſhall not contend with your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: But to morrow, in the name of good Reaſon, we claim as our own. 'Tis indiſpenſibly due to our Charity. Look therefore you propoſe to receive us with as little uneaſineſs as we can expect from a Lady in your Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances! So, without ſtaying for an anſwer, or making any Complements, they took their leaves in an humble and profound ſilence. She was very glad they were gone: For tho' ſhe were extreamly troubled at the news her Brother ſent her of the deſperate
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:99196:65"/>
condition he lay ſo long under, thro' the largeneſs and number of his Wounds; yet ſhe was overjoy'd at the certain knowledge of his Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very: So that if they had ſtay'd any conſiderable time, ſhe cou'd not have maintain'd that ſorrowful Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance with which ſhe at firſt receiv'd 'em, to the end of the Chapter: And, if ſhe had not; 'twou'd direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have croſs'd <hi>Bellamant</hi>'s deſign of having his Death believ'd in <hi>France,</hi> as well as here: To which end, he writ to her to put on Mourning, and all outward ſhew of Grief, for the loſs of an only Brother: And withall, advis'd her, to make what convenient haſte ſhe cou'd to <hi>England;</hi> all which ſhe moſt punctually obſerv'd: As <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietta</hi> did her Brother <hi>Worthygrace</hi>'s here; who, in leſs than a weeks time, had ſo well founded the depths of <hi>Philandra</hi>'s Heart; that ſhe perceiv'd, <hi>Philandra</hi> was clearly for rewarding the ſurvivor in the Duel; had there been any, as ſhe ſuppos'd there was not; with the enjoyment of her Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Eſtate. Upon which, to make
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:99196:66"/>
a ſure bargain for her Brother, not knowing that his Heart was now o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe engag'd, ſhe made an ouvert Relation to <hi>Philandra,</hi> of the whole Buſineſs; not ſo much as concealing her own Sex. How, (<hi>cry'd</hi> Philandra, <hi>in a tranſport of joy, not to be equall'd or Counterfeited but by her ſelf.</hi>) Does that great and Generous Soul ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and Actuate the Body of your dear Brother and my Lover!— And, are you not <hi>Horatio?</hi> who are you then? I am call'd <hi>Henrietta,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>(reply'd ſhe)</hi> only Siſter to <hi>Worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace;</hi> who is now in <hi>France,</hi> waiting till the Tide of State turn; or to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his pardon: which <hi>(alas!)</hi> I think, is not in humane proſpect. O! might I but ſee him once more e're I dy'd (ſaid <hi>Philandra</hi>) if ſeeing him muſt be <hi>All,</hi> I then ſhou'd go con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to my Grave. That's as your Love or Intereſt ſhall inſtruct you, Madam, (reply'd <hi>Henrietta</hi>) but I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hope you'll conſult the firſt only. But (poſſibly) he has forgot me now: Or, which is worſe, may have ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miſtreſs. I doubt not, Madam,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:99196:66"/>
(reply'd <hi>Henrietta</hi>) to ſatisfie you of the contrary within theſe few weeks; and to ſhew you his moſt grateful ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgements, under his own hand and ſeal, of ſo great and unexpected a favour as you have promis'd. In the mean time, I beg your Ladyſhip will ſtill receive me as my Brother <hi>Horatio,</hi> the better to continue the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of his Death. That, Madam (return'd <hi>Philandra</hi>) is but neceſſary to his greater ſecurity.</p>
            <p>As they were thus concluding on matters between 'em, Sir <hi>Blunder Slouch</hi> led in the feign'd <hi>Arabella</hi> to 'em: Whom aſſoon as <hi>Philandra</hi> ſaw, ſhe whiſper'd to <hi>Henrietta, This is the Lady</hi> Arabella, <hi>Siſter to the Lord</hi> Bellamant. <hi>Be cautious in your Diſcourſe!</hi> She then receiv'd and embrac'd the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>oated Lord, with a great deal of reſpect and tenderneſs: Who return'd her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements and Careſſes with equal Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony and Ardour. Telling her, he was now come to be happy for a week or more in her admir'd Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. The two Contrefeits then ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted each other; after which <hi>Philandra</hi> told the feign'd <hi>Arabella,</hi> that it was
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:99196:67"/>
               <hi>Horatio</hi> younger Brother to <hi>Worthy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>grace,</hi> whom then ſhe ſaw: And begg'd, that the fatal effects ef their Brother's Gallantry might not give them any reſentments againſt each other. Upon which they renew'd their Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ending with a Generous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion of each others loſs in two ſuch brave Men and ſo near Relations. Then they din'd together; at that time entertaining themſelves at Sir <hi>Blunder</hi>'s coſt; that was in their Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery on him: which (perhaps) he would have bought off at the price of half a ſcore Dinners. But however <hi>Bella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant</hi> appear'd pleaſant in Diſcourſe, his thoughts were very troubleſome; he never took his Eyes from <hi>Horatio</hi>'s Face, unleſs when they encounter'd his: and then, with a <hi>Woman's Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty,</hi> he wou'd let fall his, and (it may be) with a bluſh, which t'other cou'd not avoid taking notice of to her ſelf. Now it was not Love bat Jealouſie that fix'd <hi>Bellamant</hi>'s Eyes on <hi>Horatio,</hi> imagining, that the <hi>young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> Brother was now come to Rival him in <hi>Philandra:</hi> yet he rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd that ſhe might miſtake his Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:99196:67"/>
for thoſe of Love; which luckily for him ſhe did. After a modeſt Grace - cup, they fell into Cabals, <hi>Arabella</hi> and <hi>Philandra, Horatio</hi> and Sir <hi>Blunder, Arabella</hi>'s Gentlewoman and <hi>Horatio</hi>'s Companion, entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing each other in Pairs. When <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamant,</hi> to try if he had any reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able grounds for his Jealouſie, enter'd on a deſign the moſt odd and leaſt practicable that, perhaps, you have heard of: for, miſtaking <hi>Henrietta</hi> for her younger Brother, he took occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſpeak ſo obligingly of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Horatio</hi>'s Perſon, Meen, and Converſation, to <hi>Philandra,</hi> that ſhe cou'd not doubt, that it proceeded from the immediate Paſſion of Love. And, to ſpeak juſtly of her, though <hi>Henrietta</hi> had different Charms in her Face, Perſon, and in all her Actions, yet ſhe had as many and as great as <hi>Philandra</hi> or the real <hi>Arabella.</hi> Madam, (<hi>ſaid</hi> Philandra <hi>to</hi> Bellamant,) Your Ladyſhip ſpeaks ſo ſenſibly of this Gentleman's Perfections, that I have ſome reaſon to believe you cou'd love him moſt paſſionately. Poſſibly, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, <hi>return'd he,</hi> if there were any
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:99196:68"/>
proſpect of his kind return to ſuch thoughts as you ſeem to entertain; &amp; that it were not to invade your juſt Prerogative of Empire over the Hearts of all the deſertful Men, I ſhould not bluſh to own, that I have no common Reſpect for a Perſon of his Merits. 'Tis enough, <hi>replied</hi> Philandra, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly thank your Honour, Madam, for ſo free a Confeſſion: And ſhall eſteem myſelf infinitely happy, if your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip will uſe me as an Inſtrument in the uniting two ſuch generous Hearts. Be confident of me, I beſeech your Ladiſhip, <hi>continued ſhe,</hi> and be eaſie, for I will ſo manage this Affair, that he ſhall make his Addreſſes to your Ladiſhip. I perceiv'd and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Diſcourſes of your Eyes on either ſide, whilſt at Dinner. Let not my Modeſty ſuffer, I conjure you, Madam, <hi>ſaid the feign'd</hi> Arabella, for I had rather die in Deſpair. Truſt my Conduct, Madam, <hi>return'd</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra, it ſhall not coſt you a Bluſh more, than what the Diſcourſe of his Paſſion may occaſion. While the Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi> was thus pretending a Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for <hi>Horatio,</hi> the young counterfeit
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:99196:68"/>
Spark's Eyes did often meet <hi>Bella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant</hi>'s; which he obſerv'd well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. And at the ſame time was that beautiful Youth ſpeaking very advantageouſly, but juſtly too, of the feign'd <hi>Arabella</hi>'s Excellencies to Sir <hi>Blunder Slouch;</hi> who, tho he was no great Artiſt in Love, yet imagin'd that the Youngſter had a Month's Mind to a Perſon of Honour; which, at the firſt opportunity he had, tho deſir'd to keep it ſecret, according to the invincible Treachery of his Nature, he diſcover'd to <hi>Philandra:</hi> And ſhe, after ſhe had paid her earlieſt Devoirs to the ſuppos'd <hi>Arabella,</hi> whom ſhe left in Bed, went directly to <hi>Henrietta</hi>'s Apartment, and charged her with what ſhe had learn'd from Sir <hi>Blunder Slouch.</hi> She cou'd not but admire the Secrecy and Integrity of that Knight; nor did ſhe deny, that ſhe had ſaid all ſhe cou'd think in praiſe of that beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Creature. And all, dear Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, <hi>cried ſhe,</hi> comes ſhort of her Merits. Indeed I have a juſt reaſon to thank Heaven that ſhe is not a <hi>Man.</hi> This is as I wou'd have it, <hi>ſaid</hi> Philandra, for ſhe is paſſionately
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:99196:69"/>
in love with you: and I muſt ſee your Hearts and Hands united in the Holy Bands of Matrimony, (an't ſhall pleaſe you, Sir.) Why, you rave <hi>Philandra, ſaid ſhe,</hi> Do you know who, and what I am? Yes, you are the Charming <hi>Henrietta, replied</hi> Philandra, Siſter to my dear <hi>Worthygrace,</hi> and Woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. And, <hi>interrupted</hi> Henrietta, would you have the ſeeming Brother of <hi>Worthygrace</hi> marry with the Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi>'s real Siſter? Why, there's the jeſt and the earneſt on't; <hi>reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Philandra, for it will give the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter countenance to the Report of your Brother's Death. But, conſider, I remind you, <hi>ſaid</hi> Henrietta, that I am meer Womankind. I do ſo; <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied</hi> Philandra, and there will be the pleaſure on't, to ſee how ſhe will bear the loſs of her Expectation in you. Ah, <hi>cry'd</hi> Henrietta, but, by your Pardon, Madam, (methinks) that wou'd be ſomewhat barbarous, and a great Indignity to a Perſon of her Quality. Barbarous! <hi>ſaid</hi> Philandra, not at all, Child: For, being both of one Sex, the Marriage is void of courſe. And as for the Indignity, in
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:99196:69"/>
my Opinion, 'tis none: 'twill only be look'd on as a Condeſcenſion in you to pleaſure her: Beſides, we'll find out ſome Trick or other to part you, without diſcovering your Sex to her. Come, come, <hi>(purſued ſhe)</hi> it muſt be done; I am reſolv'd on't. Well, dear Madam, (<hi>return'd</hi> Henrietta) to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, but (let me own it, with Pardon) more particularly to ſerve my Brother, I will begin the Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to the Lady <hi>Arabella.</hi> This was agreed, and proceeded on that very day: and the fair Counterfeit found he ſhou'd have no hard Siege of his beautiful Miſtreſs's Heart. I think at the third Approach he made to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it, ſhe began a Parley; at the end of which ſhe ſurrender'd on Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. Married then they were, but very privately, and with no So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity or Mirth more than uſual, unleſs it were the addition of two or three Country-Fidles, and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſeeing Sir <hi>Blunder</hi> very beſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Drunk. At night <hi>Arabella</hi> was put to Bed, trembling for fear of a Diſcovery of his Sex; being partly undreſs'd by <hi>Philandra</hi>'s fair Hands.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:99196:70"/>
You may imagine what a fine conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhe was in, when <hi>Philandra</hi> came to finger her Neck, near the place of her No-bubbies: 'twas then ſhe was forc'd to pretend ſhe was ready to ſwoon away, with a faint and almoſt dying Voice, begging <hi>Philandra</hi> and the reſt of the Females, to give her leave to put her ſelf to Bed; which, with ſome difficulty, they permitted her: where ſhe laid her ſelf down cloſe to the Bed-poſt; a very hopeful Bride. But the Bridegroom ſcap'd better, for there was no man to undreſs him, but Sir <hi>Blunder,</hi> who had drunk himſelf out of that Office. The Bridegroom no ſooner came into Bed, but as <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra</hi> had inſtructed him, he took the Bride about the neck, and, (as it were) forc'd a kiſs, and then the Company left 'em to themſelves, for that night; and each miſtaking the others Sex; after ſome comical re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections to themſelves, on their odd and haſty Marriage, fell faſt aſleep. <hi>Bellamant</hi> with the pleaſure to think that he had now defeated <hi>Philandra</hi> of a ſecond Lover; and <hi>Henrietta</hi> with the ſatisfaction that this Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:99196:70"/>
knot might be unty'd when ever ſhe pleas'd.</p>
            <p>Between Seven and Eight the next morning, the fair Bridegroom ask'd his Bride how ſhe had ſlept that night? To which ſhe reply'd, very well, and quietly, I thank you, Sir; he wiſh'd her then a good morrow, which ſhe return'd to him; and not long after he roſe, leaving the Bride the opportunity of dreſſing her ſelf; which I can aſſure you was then very obliging. About half an hour after came in the fulſom meſs of Cawdles, with Potions of Tent, and Malaga; which, whether ſhe taſted or no, I was not curious to enquire. After Dinner they took Coach, as they had contriv'd with <hi>Philandra;</hi> and ſeem'd to drive for <hi>London,</hi> taking their leave of Sir <hi>Blunder,</hi> who in leſs than an hour went directly for the Town, while they return'd a contrary way to <hi>Philandra.</hi> This was done to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the trouble of ſo many viſits from all their friends and acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance that were known to Sir <hi>Blunder,</hi> whom they were ſure he wou'd other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have ſent. At <hi>Philandra</hi>'s then
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:99196:71"/>
they paſs'd two nights more, almoſt in the ſtate of innocence; only <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamant</hi> wou'd be now and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting on the meſs of bawdery that <hi>Philandra,</hi> and the other Women-Creatures entertain'd him with, after the Sack poſſet, while they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing him on the Wedding-Night; miſtaking him for the true <hi>Arabella;</hi> which did ſometimes but too well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind him of his Sex. And doubtleſs had he known what excellent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to work upon he had lying by him, all thoſe three nights, he wou'd have gone near to have diſcover'd, and ſo perhaps to have loſt himſelf in ſearch of ſuch treaſures. The third morning when the Beautiful young Bridegroom was taking a walk about the grounds, <hi>Philandra</hi> came to pay her reſpects to the Bride; juſt as by good fortune ſhe was dreſs'd, and no body with her, but her Page in Woman's Cloaths, who paſs'd for her ſhe Attendant. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra</hi> ſeem'd to deſire ſome private Conference with her, on which, the Attendant withdrew. Madam, ſaid <hi>Philandra,</hi> your Ladyſhip puts me quite out of conceit with marriage;
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:99196:71"/>
for I have obſerv'd, that ever ſince you have been more than uſually me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly. I beg your Honour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to let me know what it is that diſlikes you in this State, and what you find more than heretofore plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, if any ſuch thing there be. Ah, <hi>Philandra,</hi> reply'd the ſuppos'd <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella,</hi> I can eaſily ſay what diſlikes me. I have ſold my Liberty, <hi>Philandra,</hi> and to one, who I fear, had before engag'd his heart to another. He's Young, and Beautiful, 'tis true, and that he is a Man I cannot doubt, by outward appearance; but—I have heretofore dream'd of—I know not what—Joys, that we marry'd folks ſhou'd be fed with, 'till we e'en ſurfeited of 'em; but I find he has no other in ſtore for me, than a good morrow, or good night. Or an inſipid out 'o bed breakfaſt of Cawdles, and Sack, interrupted <hi>Philandra.</hi> Ay, <hi>Philandra,</hi> reply'd <hi>Arabella,</hi> this is all the pleaſure I find in it. Poor <hi>Lady,</hi> cry'd <hi>Philandra,</hi> this is a heavy dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Tale—Good Heaven guard me from ſuch a fool of a Husband. Why, pray, Madam, ask'd the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:99196:72"/>
Bride, what more wou'd you expect from your Husband? Poor Dear Soul, return'd <hi>Philandra,</hi> what more? why—At leaſt a thouſand kiſſes eve y day, and one continu'd Embrace every night; or ſo many ſo ſuddainly repeated, that they ſhou'd ſeem but one. Alas, Madam, return'd the Bride, this were enough to make any Man's arms, back, and heart ake; beſides, I ſhou'd fear he wou'd ſtifle us both. Not to conſider the loſs of ſleep, which wou'd diſcompoſe and unfit us for the next day's Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Sleep, Converſation, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted t'other; why, my Dear, ſleep ought to be baniſh'd, at leaſt, all the firſt month, unleſs, from five or ſix in the morning, till eleven or twelve at noon. And no converſation ought in reaſon or modeſty to be expected by any of their Friends or Acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but juſt in a morning's viſit, or at Dinner, and Supper; the reſt of the day ought to be ſacred to Love, and the Happy Pair in Lonely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats, Pleaſant Gardens, Cool Grot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to's, and Shady Groves. Bleſs me, Madam, cry'd <hi>Arabella,</hi> what a <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules</hi>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:99196:72"/>
of a Husband muſt yours be? Nay, Madam, pardon me, ſaid <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra,</hi> I do not mean that only ſuch a one wou'd ſatisfie me, but I ſuppoſe this the Spark's duty for the whole honey-moon. I wonder, Madam, ſaid the Bride, what you wou'd do then, if you had ſuch a quiet Spark as mine, who never ſo much as touches me, nor ſpeaks after the firſt good night, 'till the next morning. Why, truly Madam, reply'd <hi>Philandra,</hi> to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous to you, I ſhou'd ſeek my ſatisfaction elſewhere. O fye, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd <hi>Arabella,</hi> I warrant you wou'd not commit that Sin for the Univerſe. No, Madam, anſwer'd t'other, 'tis my dull niggardly Husband that ſtarves me at home, who commits the Sin, in forcing me to ſeek out for my own ſuſtenance. Alas, Madam, continued ſhe, the thing is nothing in it ſelf, but pleaſure; the Crime lies in being detected of it. This indeed, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, return'd <hi>Arabella,</hi> is to me a new ſort of Doctrine; but I find it very reaſonable; how wholſome it may prove, I am yet to learn. As your food, I'll warrant it, reply'd
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:99196:73"/>
'tother, and as neceſſary; and I hope you will put it in practice with the firſt opportunity. I can't promiſe you that, return'd <hi>Arabella,</hi> 'till I have thought further on't.</p>
            <p>Immediately at the end of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe the Bridegroom enter'd; who told <hi>Arabella</hi> that he deſir'd to wait on her to her own Lodgings in Town, that Afternoon, becauſe he expected a near Kinſman of his, a young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of about Eighteen, who came from <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> almoſt on purpoſe to viſit him. And ſince her Ladyſhips Lodgings in <hi>Soho-Square,</hi> he believ'd were moſt convenient, he wou'd leave word at his own Lodgings, where his Couſin <hi>Winlove,</hi> for ſo was he call'd, might find him. I'm all obedience to your pleaſure, Sir, (reply'd <hi>Arabella.</hi>) After which, they only ſtay'd dinner with <hi>Philandra,</hi> for the Coach was made ready before: and when <hi>Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> had oblig'd her ſelf to viſit 'em as ſoon, and often as 'twas poſſible, they hurried away to <hi>Arabella</hi>'s Lodgings in Town, where he left her, and went to his own, whence he return'd, with ſome uneaſineſs, enough obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:99196:73"/>
in his face, and haſte. Madam, ſaid he, I muſt beg your Ladyſhips pardon, that I am conſtrain'd to leave you for ſome few days. I have juſt now receiv'd a Letter left at my Lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings theſe three days, that calls me immediately into <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> where my preſence is abſolutely neceſſary, to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſome part of my Eſtate. I do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your Ladyſhip I will be as expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious in the diſpatch of my Affairs as may be, that I may return the ſooner, to the greateſt happineſs I have on Earth, your Ladyſhip— But—I had almoſt forgot to beg your Ladyſhip wou'd receive my Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with the ſame kindneſs and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity you wou'd entertain me; deny him nothing, to expreſs the welcome of him—For, give me leave to ſay, Madam, tho' he is my near Relation, he is a very worthy, and finely accompliſh'd Gentleman, and indeed extreamly Beautiful; and were his hair fair, as it is exceeding black, you wou'd eaſily miſtake him for <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra,</hi> in Man's Cloaths.—Once more, pray be kind to him, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam—With this kiſs I ſeal, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:99196:74"/>
thee to the care of Heaven— Farewell, my Soul, added he, going out. Heaven keep you, Sir, ſaid ſhe, pray haſten your return—Hah! (cry'd <hi>Bellamant</hi> to himſelf) no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <hi>Arabella,</hi> when alone. Muſt I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Kinſman with the ſame kindneſs and familiarity that I wou'd entertain him? and deny him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing —I begin to have 'em in the wind—This is purſuant of that excellent Doctrine I heard preach'd to day, by my moſt Learned Miſtreſs in the Art of Love, <hi>Philandra;</hi> whom this Relation of his ſo nearly reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; that <q>were it Fair, as it is Black, I cou'd not eaſily miſtake it for <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra</hi> in Man's Cloaths—</q> I'll put all this together; and, let me ſee, what does it ſpell?— <hi>Contrivance.</hi>
Ay, that's it. Now is this little fair Devil grown malicious; and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, that I have robb'd her of the younger Brother, comes to tempt my Vertue, and Debauch me, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, (which was well put in) in the habit of a fine Spark, and then to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray me to <hi>Horatio,</hi> miſtaking me ſtill for my Siſter. And I muſt needs own,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:99196:74"/>
that I fear I am not Temptation-proof. No, no, 'tis certain I am not. Alas, alas, what will become of me then?—Why, I may thank my Petticoats for all the lewdneſs that is like to enſue—Oh, Petticoat, Petticoat, how attractive thou art of all Vices?—Why, faith now, he was much in the right on't; only in this he miſtook, that it was <hi>Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi>'s Revenge. For, the Deſign was to take the ſuppos'd <hi>Arabella</hi> in Bed with the pretended <hi>Winlove,</hi> to give the feign'd <hi>Horatio</hi> a <hi>ſeeming juſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of parting with her. <hi>Bellamant</hi> was raviſh'd with the deſign which he perceiv'd <hi>Philandra</hi> had of ruining her ſelf; and with impatience ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected when ſhe wou'd begin it. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, he ſpent that night very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly, with his two Friends, who carry'd him out of the fatal Field, over a Bottle or Two. And the next day, about Eleven, one of her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, for now 'tis <hi>Arabella</hi> again; came to acquaint her, that one Mr. <hi>Winlove</hi> enquir'd for his Maſter; upon which, ſhe ſent the Servant to wait on him in, and came down ſtairs her
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:99196:75"/>
ſelf to receive him. The treachery there began with a kiſs too— Then after having enquir'd of his Couſin's health, and when ſhe expected his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn? And having highly, tho' not ſufficiently complemented her Beauty, (at which he ſeem'd as much aſtoniſh'd as ſhe was, at the ſtrange alteration the change of habit, and other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſes had made of the Perſon of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra,</hi> who had on a Black Perruke, had black'd her eye-brows, and eye-lids, and had left a kind of ſhadow on her upper Lip, as if ſhe had been newly ſhav'd) <hi>Winlove</hi> was for taking his leave, which by no means his Lady Couſin wou'd permit; (deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a happier Night than ordinary) and in ſhort, prevail'd with him to ſtay Dinner; when he fell afreſh into large Encomiums of her Beauty; ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to think that his Couſin was, and muſt be the only happy man in the World, in the enjoyment of ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections as her Ladyſhips, of which, he was Eternally to be debarr'd. She told him, ſhe believ'd it was in his power to make himſelf as happy as his Couſin. <hi>Winlove</hi> was a little
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:99196:75"/>
ſurpriz'd at that anſwer of hers; yet <hi>taking Courage, threw at all; approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng her more cloſely,</hi> and kiſſing her, till <hi>her Face was all Feaver, and her Eyes were all Flame</hi> Then, by a ſeeming force ſhe got from him, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew into the next room. I ſee, ſaid <hi>Philandra</hi> to her ſelf, my Documents have pretty well taken root in her, ſhe warms apace, I muſt not let her Cool. Saying ſo, he purſu'd her into the next Room, where he wou'd have renew'd his Careſſes. But ſhe in a languiſhing tone, and hiding her face, told him, that tho' her Husband had deſir'd her to deny him nothing; as indeed ſhe cou'd not deny him any thing; yet ſhe begg'd ſhe might have a little reſpite to bethink her ſelf what ſhe was going to do. Nay, Madam, <hi>(return'd he)</hi> that's the way to ruine my Hopes: However, we'll Sup toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if you pleaſe; and ſo contrive matters that no notice may be taken of the Happineſs which I hope your Ladiſhip deſigns me afterwards. They did ſo, and things were order'd ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; that is, he was put to Bed in the next Room on the ſame Floor
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:99196:76"/>
to her: And <hi>Arabella</hi>'s Page in Woman's Cloaths double-lock'd the Door upon him: About an hour after <hi>Arabella</hi> unlock'd it, thinking every Moment a Month till the Houſe were ſilent; ſo near did <hi>Bellamant</hi> apprehend his Happineſs; which he wou'd not ha' let ſlip that Night for all hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Eſtate, I fancy. But we muſt yet ſuppoſe him <hi>Arabella</hi> a little while, and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra Winelove:</hi> No ſooner then had <hi>Arabella</hi> got into Bed, than <hi>Winelove</hi> was in her Chamber, and had lock'd the Door; and you may believe did not ſtand long on the cold Floor. Madam, <hi>(ſaid he, turning to her,)</hi> this Night were worth Immortality, had I not drank too much at Supper: but the Morning ſhall pay us the Arrears of the preſent. —How, Sir! <hi>(cry'd ſhe)</hi> and do you too deceive my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation? — Nay, then, I'm ſure my Husband and you are of the ſame Family, and <hi>too</hi> nearly related. Why, ay, Madam, (<hi>return'd</hi> Winlove,) this Conſcience makes Cowards, and Fools Eunuchs: Or Women of you, (<hi>interrupted</hi> Arabella,) I'm reſolv'd I will know if y'are a Man; <hi>(purſu'd
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:99196:76"/>
ſhe, embracing her very ſtrictly.)</hi> O, <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra, (cry'd he, ſpeaking in a more Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine Tone,)</hi> 'tis now <hi>my</hi> turn to play the Man, and revenge my ſelf upon you for all my Sufferings, that yet were not worth this raviſhing killing Moment, which ſure I can't out-live! —Then cou'd not he ſpeak one word more for a whole moment or two: After he call'd her <hi>Philandra,</hi> the poor Soul was ſo amaz'd, or overjoy'd, that ſhe did not, or (may be) cou'd not or wou'd not ſpeak one word; till at laſt he had juſt liberty to ſay, Now, Madam, you ſhall find that neither Night nor Morning ſhall be indebted to me. At which, ſhe cried out, O Heavens! my Lord, are you then <hi>reſolv'd</hi> to ruine me? —And now, both were Tongue-tied again: About 4 a clock in the morning, <hi>Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra,</hi> with a thouſand Kiſſes and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Embraces, and with Tears in her Eyes, ſaid to him, Tho', my Lord, you have now by my own fooliſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triguing, rifled me of the greateſt Treaſure, my Honour, and graſp'd all thoſe Joys at once, for which you ſtrove ſo long, ſo often, and ſo fatal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:99196:77"/>
You will not leave me thus na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſpoil'd of all that is valuable. May not I hope, that you will reſtore what you have taken from me, my Honour? I now beg it of you as an Act of Humanity, and becoming your accuſtom'd Generoſity and Goodneſs. Will you not marry me, my Lord? Can you doubt it, Madam? <hi>reply'd he, by way of Interrogation.</hi> Let me firſt be clear of the Death of that brave Man; and then, my Life, we'll be as Happy as 'tis poſſible. She then proceeded to ask his Pardon, that ſhe had deſign'd to betray <hi>Arabella</hi> to <hi>Horatio,</hi> who wou'd have taken that occaſion to part with her, ſtill ſuppoſing him to be <hi>Arabella.</hi> And added, that <hi>Horatio</hi> wou'd be there at five that Morning, or ſoon after. <hi>Bellamant</hi> ſmil'd, and told her, he was more oblig'd to <hi>them for their Plot,</hi> than he was to his Anceſtors for his Honour and Eſtate: And, after he had taken <hi>a fair Leave of her,</hi> ſhe return'd to Bed in the next Room, <hi>from the place of Execution;</hi> without diſcovering the pretended <hi>Horatio</hi>'s Sex, leſt he ſhou'd forſake her, and
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:99196:77"/>
marry <hi>Henrietta,</hi> whoſe Charms ſhe was but too well acquainted with for her eaſe. Nor wou'd ſhe rid <hi>Bella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant</hi> of his troubleſome Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the ſuppos'd Death of <hi>Worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace,</hi> till ſhe had ſecur'd him to her ſelf by Marriage.</p>
            <p>Between five and ſix that morning <hi>Horatio</hi> came to his Lady's Lodgings, as was expected; and went directly up Stairs to her Bed-chamber, which he enter'd very ſoftly, and found her faſt aſleep, and all alone; for the Key was left deſignedly on the out ſide. He did not deſire to wake her by any means, and therefore retreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as ſilently as he enter'd, locking the Door after him. Thence he came to the next Room, where <hi>Winlove</hi> lay, the Door of which he found double lock'd, and the Key without, which he turn'd, and ſtole in with the leaſt noiſe imaginable: coming to the Bed-ſide, he found her in a dead Sleep too; and being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to diſturb her, was returning down Stairs; and going to lock the Door, made ſo much noiſe as waken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her. Who's there? (<hi>ask'd</hi> Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra.)
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:99196:78"/>
Softly, ſoftly, <hi>(return'd</hi> Hora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, <hi>creeping towards her,)</hi> —Will you riſe? I will juſt now, <hi>(reply'd ſhe,)</hi> getting up, and dreſſing So toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they went to the Park, where they took a round or two, till 'twas about eight a clock. Thence they went to a Coffee-houſe, where they drunk three or four Diſhes of Choco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let apiece: then they adjourn'd to <hi>Locket</hi>'s, where whil'ſt their little Break-faſt or Dinner was preparing, <hi>Henrietta</hi> began to ask Queſtions, more to ſatisfie her own Curioſity, than to keep t'other awake, tho it were very neceſſary to talk to her leſt ſhe ſhou'd ha' ſlept: Prithee, <hi>(ſaid ſhe)</hi> and without any Preface, let me know the ſucceſs of laſt Night's Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture; Is ſhe obſtinately Vertuous, or are there any hopes of our Parting? Ah! no; (<hi>reply'd</hi> Philandra,) ſhe's Chaſt as Ice, and true to your Bed as the Load-ſtone to its Point. 'Tis true, <hi>(purſu'd ſhe)</hi> after a whole Day's Courtſhip, I at laſt prevail'd; and, as I thought, had reach'd my end; for I lay with her in her own Bed, from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leven to four; But— Nay, that's
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:99196:78"/>
enough; (<hi>interrupted</hi> Henrietta.) Hold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pray hear me out; <hi>(cry'd t'other,)</hi> I had no ſooner taken her in my Arms, than ſhe ſigh'd and wept, and cry'd, Ah me! what do you mean <hi>Philandra?</hi> you can't carry the Cheat on in <hi>Bed</hi> I'm ſure. Heaven, (ſaid I, in my thoughts) wou'd thou wou'dſt make me a Man this moment! This I wiſh'd, that I might ha' ſerv'd thee, my dear <hi>Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etta.</hi> And pleaſure yourſelf, Madam, (<hi>return'd</hi> Henrietta.) But (it ſeems) ſhe knew you then? Ay, ay, knew me, as I <hi>am;</hi> knew me <hi>Philandra:</hi> knew me to be <hi>Womankind,</hi> or I dare engage I had ne'er come ſo near her. But (O!) when I firſt embrac'd the poor dear Creature, how it did <hi>tremble!</hi> how ſhort it drew its breath! and the poor Heart of it did beat ſo very faſt and loud, that though the Larum of my Watch beat that very moment, I yet cou'd hear the Motion of its Heart diſtinctly above t'other. Ay! (<hi>ſaid</hi> Henrietta) that's odd and ſtrange: Prithee, what ſhou'd cauſe it? Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, I imagine (<hi>reply'd</hi> Philandra) to find me play my part ſo vigorouſly and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:99196:79"/>
ſo much to the life. But (<hi>ask'd</hi> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietta) ſince ſhe knew you to be <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra,</hi> what occaſion'd you to leave her Bed before I came? O, Madam, <hi>(reply'd t'other)</hi> that was to blind your Ladiſhip's Attendants, who ſaw me go to Bed in the Room where you found me; who wou'd have thought it very impudent in her to find ſhe had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a young Spark to her Bed; for which ſhe miſtook me. I can but ſmile (<hi>ſaid</hi> Henrietta) to think, how finely you had been ſerv'd, if inſtead of the Siſter you had met the Brother there. To anſwer you wantonly to your Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, (<hi>return'd</hi> Philandra) I muſt tell you, had my Lord been living, and there, he wou'd ha' done me Knight's Service. But, after all this, (<hi>ſaid</hi> Henrietta) I cannot any longer perſonate her Bridegroom, eſpecially in <hi>Bed.</hi> You need not, (<hi>reply'd</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landra) do you continue at my Houſe, and I will keep her in her Lodgings, for I have engag'd to wait on her eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other day till you return; which you may defer this month, if you pleaſe. It muſt be ſo, (<hi>reply'd</hi> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietta.)
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:99196:79"/>
The Table was then cover'd, and immediately after two or three Diſhes were ſerv'd in, which were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Dinner: By the ſtrength of which they ventur'd to travel ſeven or eight Miles from the Town in their own eaſie Coach. Mean while <hi>Arabella,</hi> as ſoon as her Ladiſhip was dreſs'd, ſent for her two Friends to take a Dinner and a Bottle with her; who came preciſely at the hour: ſo to dinner they went, and her Ladiſhip eat and drank, as if ſhe had been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready quick with three Children, and were to feed Them and her ſelf: for (to ſay truth) ſhe had taken a great deal of pains. That day and night he enjoy'd himſelf with his drinking Friends; but the next was Loves and <hi>Philandra</hi>'s. A very pretty courſe of life this Loving and Drinking is, in my Opinion; which he continu'd for above a Fortnight; conſecrating one day and night to his Miſtreſs, and the next to his Friends and the merry Bottle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Worthygrace</hi> in the mean time had made very conſiderable Advances in
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:99196:80"/>
the Eſteem of the real <hi>Arabella;</hi> he found her inclinable enough to favour his Suit: The only Obſtacle ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, was, That ſhe wou'd ſee her Brother's Death reveng'd e'er ſhe cou'd be perfectly Happy in <hi>any State:</hi> And in order to that, ſhe told them, ſhe wou'd leave <hi>France</hi> in three or four days. To which he return'd, That he wou'd certainly leave it at the ſame time; ſince, when ſhe was gone, he had no longer any buſineſs or pleaſure there. And beſides, did ſolemnly oblige himſelf to ſhew her the Unhappy Man who kill'd her Brother, and to help her in her Revenge upon him. This Overture of his ſeem'd to affect her very much: And ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented he ſhou'd accompany her to <hi>England;</hi> which he did, after they had recommended all their Friends there to Heaven's Protection. And on that very day they left <hi>Paris</hi> there came a Letter from <hi>Henrietta,</hi> with an account of all her Tranſactions, ſince ſhe had taken upon her the Perſon of her younger Brother: but he did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this, till he had been near a Fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:99196:80"/>
here. As ſoon as they ſet foot on <hi>Engliſh</hi> ground, they made all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible haſte to Town; and happen'd to come to <hi>Bellamant</hi>'s Lodgings that ſame day on which <hi>Philandra</hi> came to viſit him in her own wonted Habit. 'Twas about three a clock in the Afternoon, when <hi>Arabella</hi> whiſpering <hi>Bellamant</hi>'s Petticoated Page in the Ear, ask'd, if his Lord were within; who reply'd Yes, Madam; and knowing her very well, ran to acquaint <hi>Bellamant,</hi> who was ſomewhat buſie with <hi>Philandra,</hi> that a Gentleman and a Lady deſir'd to ſpeak with her Ladiſhip. He wou'd not tell his ſuppos'd Lady, that 'twas <hi>Arabella,</hi> leſt <hi>Philandra</hi> ſhou'd appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that he knew 'twas <hi>Bellamant</hi> whom he had ſeen in Bed with her more than once. Shew 'em into the Parlour, (<hi>ſaid</hi> Bellamant) I'll wait on 'em inſtantly. I can't imagine who they ſhould be, (<hi>added he,</hi> to Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra.) The Page led 'em into the Parlour, and left 'em together. Now, Madam, ſaid <hi>Worthygrace,</hi> I do keep the promiſe I made to your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, for you ſee in me the unhappy
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:99196:81"/>
man that kill'd my Lord, your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and I beſeech you proſecute me with all the rigour of the Law, that I may not live in deſpair. 'Tis hard, Sir, return'd ſhe, I ſee your Love, and our unequal misfortunes, but here comes one that may put an end to 'em, I hope. At that word, <hi>Bellamant,</hi> and <hi>Philandra</hi> enter'd.—All of 'em at the ſight of each other, ſtood fix'd, and look'd like their own Monuments. <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamant</hi> having a preſence of mind above the reſt, was the firſt that broke the Charm; who, crying out, O my Lord, and dear Brother, are you yet among the Living? ran to <hi>Arabella,</hi> and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing and kiſſing her cheeks, whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd to her at the ſame time, that ſhe ſhou'd own her ſelf <hi>Bellamant.</hi> My dear <hi>Arabella,</hi> ſaid his Siſter, embracing him again, how happy am I to ſee thee once more. Ah, <hi>Philandra, purſu'd ſhe,</hi> I hope you will at laſt put an end to our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, in your choice of one of us; at which, <hi>Philandra</hi> bluſh'd, and wept. Nay, my Lord, return'd <hi>Worthygrace,</hi> I am otherwiſe engag'd, you may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; for tho' I have hitherto miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:99196:81"/>
your Lordſhip for the Lady your Siſter, I muſt continue my addreſs to her; and I hope your Lordſhip is ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that my paſſion is real. Ay, Sir, reply'd <hi>Arabella,</hi> ſtill perſonating her Brother; my Siſter has the misfortune to be very like me, and I doubt not that your paſſion deſign'd for her is real; Siſter <hi>(continu'd ſhe)</hi> let me com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this Gentleman to your deareſt thoughts. Saying ſo, ſhe joyn'd their hands. Do you conſent to make me happy, Madam? (ſaid <hi>Worthygrace,</hi> to his Rival that was) I can't do better Sir, than to follow the advice of my honour'd Brother, ſaid <hi>Bellamant.</hi> Well, Siſter, return'd <hi>Arabella,</hi> for your kind complaiſance, I will add 5000 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> to your Fortune, and make it up Thirty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds. Your Lordſhip ever was my moſt obliging and affectionate Brother (reply'd <hi>Bellamant.) Philandra</hi> all this while did not know how to behave her ſelf; ſometimes ſhe was ready to burſt with envy, to ſee <hi>Worthygrace</hi> forſake her, for <hi>Arabella;</hi> and ſometimes with laughter, to ſee how neatly the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Siſter play'd a contrary part.
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:99196:82"/>
At laſt ſhe broke ſilence, and ſaid, I am happy beyond <hi>Expectation, Hope, or Wiſh,</hi> my Lord, to ſee your Lordſhip, and this Honourable Gentleman living, and ſo happily united. They both Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, and thank'd her. I dare ſay my Lord, ſaid <hi>Bellamant</hi> to <hi>Arabella,</hi> your Lordſhip is horribly aſham'd, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of your Petticoats. You may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of it, reply'd ſhe. To morrow your Lordſhip will appear like your ſelf, I hope, return'd <hi>Bellamant.</hi> I wiſh my Lord, ſaid <hi>Worthygraee</hi> to <hi>Arabella,</hi> that your Lordſhip had ſo appear'd in <hi>Paris.</hi> But then I ſuppoſe you had loſt all the divertée your Lordſhip has had with my paſſion, miſtaking you for the Lady your Siſter. Ay, Sir, return'd <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabella,</hi> you have ſpoken my thoughts. Sir, ſaid <hi>Philandra</hi> to <hi>Worthygrace,</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there is an acquaintance of yours at my Country-houſe, whom I will wait on hither to morrow.—Mean while, purſu'd ſhe, to <hi>Arabella,</hi> my Lord, I humbly take my leave. I am your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhips Servant, added ſhe to <hi>Bella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant,</hi> Mr. <hi>Worthygrace,</hi> your Servant. They all waited on her to her Coach,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:99196:82"/>
and <hi>Worthygrace</hi> wou'd needs attend her home, that ſhe might not be alone, and that he might the ſooner ſee his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. <hi>Henrietta</hi> expreſs'd a great deal of ſatisfaction at the ſight of her Brother, after ſo long an abſence; nor was he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind hand in his expreſſions <hi>of joy at the ſight of her; Philandra</hi> only was diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, who found ſhe ſhou'd dye an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmarry'd Widow,</hi> unleſs ſhe took up with Sir <hi>Blunder Slouch,</hi> or ſome ſuch Booby of a Hushand.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Bellamant</hi> and his Siſter were alone, ſhe wou'd fain ha' known why he had oblig'd her to perſonate him? Who reply'd, there are reaſons of State, Child, too dark for thee to pry into. Now it was only generouſly to preſerve <hi>Philandra</hi>'s Reputation unſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. Next morning <hi>Bellamant</hi> was dreſs'd like himſelf, and <hi>Arabella</hi> was as Glorious as her beſt habiliments cou'd make her; and about Ten a Clock <hi>Worthygrace, Henrietta, Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra,</hi> and Sir <hi>Blunder Slouch,</hi> who went to viſit <hi>Philandra</hi> the day before, came to Congratulate his Lordſhip's return to the Land of the Living, as he had
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:99196:83"/>
welcom'd <hi>Worthygrace</hi> to life again. To this end came <hi>Henrietta,</hi> no longer now in Man's Apparel. When the Complements on all ſides were over, <hi>Worthygrace</hi> led his Siſter to <hi>Arabella,</hi> to beg her pardon, that ſhe had thus long abus'd her with the appearance of a Man. How, cry'd <hi>Bellamant,</hi> is this the Beautiful Counterfeit that I have heard my Siſter ſpeak of? It is then in her power to make me the moſt happy of all Mankind, in receiving an heart that was made for her to command. In which I beg your aſſiſtance, Sir, added he to <hi>Worthygrace;</hi> who reply'd, that he was aſſur'd his Siſter wou'd be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd by him in any thing, eſpecially in what wou'd for ever compleat her happineſs on Earth; which ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd. Replying, I am all obedience, Sir, you are now both Father and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to me. <hi>Worthygrace</hi> then preſented her hand to <hi>Bellamant,</hi> who received it with the greateſt demonſtrations of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and joy. Now, Madam, ſaid he to <hi>Philandra,</hi> we have made your choice eaſie to you; for you can now be cruel to neither of us. I only beg
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:99196:83"/>
you will not be cruel to Sir <hi>Blunder,</hi> who has been your old and faithful Servant. I think indeed he was bound before me, and has ſerv'd out his whole Apprentiſhip of Seven Years; pray Madam make him free at laſt, we all make it our Petition to you (ſaid <hi>Worthygrace</hi> and the Ladies.) I hope, Madam <hi>Philandra,</hi> (cry'd Sir <hi>Blunder</hi>) you will at laſt take pity upon me. Ay, Knight (return'd ſhe) But— 'Tis for my own ſake, you may be confident. I am reſolv'd I will not be ſingular, among ſo many Worthy and Honourable Friends. But firſt I beg one word with your Lordſhip (added ſhe to <hi>Bellamant</hi>) who approach'd her very humbly and reſpectfully, bowing down his head to receive her whiſper—Are not you a Falſe man? (ſaid ſhe) Ay, Madam (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd he) but that is becauſe you are a True Woman.—And let me remind you, that you have had the pleaſure <hi>to make a Whore of me, and a Cuckold of my Wife.</hi> Beſides, I have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken care that your reputation ſhall not ſuffer by me—Alas (Madam purſu'd he aloud) what needed this have been whiſper'd? —She ſays Sir <hi>Blunder,</hi> ſhe will not be debarr'd the gayety of her humour, nor be confin'd to your damn'd Conventicles, nor ſmoaky City. And truly I think it is but reaſonable ſhe ſhou'd not. In good faith (reply'd Sir <hi>Blunder</hi>) ſhe ſhall have Liberty of Conſcience, if ſhe'll have me: Upon that, <hi>Bellamant</hi> gave him her hand; and Sir <hi>Blunder</hi> was the happy Man that got the City-Fortune; who indeed I think was fit for no man elſe. My Lord (ſaid <hi>Worthygrace</hi>) I will follow your generous Example, and add Ten
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:99196:84"/>
Thouſand Pounds to my Siſter's Portion, to make it Thirty Thouſand Pounds. And now I beſeech your Lordſhip (purſu'd he) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix the day that ſhall make us all happy. By this day fortnight (return'd <hi>Bellamant</hi>) we may be prepar'd for the mighty Bleſſing. This day fortnight (cry'd <hi>Philandra</hi>) I'll not ſtay an hour, but will have the honour to ſet you the Glorious Example. There is a <hi>Domine</hi> hard by I warrant you, that will oblige me ſo far. He was immediately ſent for, and they were both Executed at one blow. This day (ſaid ſhe) I challenge as mine; you are all my Gueſts, and I have already order'd a Dinner at my Country Farm, whither you all muſt go. Upon this, they inſtantly took their Coaches, and drove for the Lady <hi>Slou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che's;</hi> who, as I have heard, about Eight Months after, was fain to be brought to Bed; before the Child cou'd be Born, which was very like the Father: The Lord <hi>Bellamant</hi> was Godfather; as any Spark or Beau may be to the next, if he knows where to find her.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
